<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conversion of a sinner explained and applied from Ezek. 33. 11 ... part whereof was preached some while since at Saviours Southwark : The day of grace, discoursed of from Luke 19. 41,42 ... / by Nathaneal Vincent.</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18478119</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18478119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64955)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1644:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conversion of a sinner explained and applied from Ezek. 33. 11 ... part whereof was preached some while since at Saviours Southwark : The day of grace, discoursed of from Luke 19. 41,42 ... / by Nathaneal Vincent.</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: all lacking after "Conversion of a sinner"; cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezekiel XXXIII, 11 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Conversion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:1"/>
            <p>THE CONVERSION OF A SINNER Explained and Applied, FROM</p>
            <bibl>Ezek. 33. 11.</bibl>
            <q>Turn ye, turn ye, from your evil wayes; for why will ye die, O houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Part whereof was preached ſome while ſince at Saviours <hi>Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Day of Grace, DISCOURSED OF FROM</p>
            <bibl>Luke 19. 41, 42.</bibl>
            <q>If thou hadst known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong to thy peace! But now they are hid from thine eyes.</q>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Vincent,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkburſt,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Bible</hi> on <hi>London-Brdge,</hi> under the Gate, 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:2"/>
            <head>The Dedication. To his Sacred and moſt Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty, the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, the KING of KINGS, and LORD of LORDS; who is much more above the higheſt Potentates and Emperors in the World, than they are above their meaneſt Slaves!</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Almighty Lord!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O Thee I dedicate my Book, to whom I have devoted my ſelf, all that is good therein, it is thy own; and if it do any good, to Thee I muſt aſcribe the praiſe. The In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nt indeed might be aſhamed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged,
<pb facs="tcp:107824:3"/> if he did not know that thou canſt work as well by weak means as by ſtrong; nay, ſometimes thou makeſt choice of weak on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that fleſh may not glory, but the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the power may be of thee alone.</p>
            <p>It was moſt free and rich Grace, (which Eternity it ſelf will be ſhort enough to admire and adore) that I my ſelf was pitied, who once lay as much polluted in my blood as any other; who had run ſo far in the broad way, and had ſinn'd my ſelf ſo neer the deſtruction which is everlaſting! But if I am not only made a Convert, but alſo made uſe of to convert o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, my obligation will be hightned, which is infinitely vaſt already, to ſhew forth thy praiſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis the deſire of my ſoul, O Lord! that thy Kingdom may be advanced, and that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion which ſin and Satan have uſurped may be overthrown. Since thy yoak is eaſie and thy government ſo ſweet, ſo gracious, why ſhould not thy ſubjects alſo be moſt numerous? Gird thy ſword upon thy thing, Oh, moſt mighty one! and ride forth conquering and to conquer; and thy right hand ſhall teach thee terrible things. Let thine arrows be ſharp, and thy Word pierce like a two-edged ſword; and let the whole world, either by converſion or ſubverſion, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſpecially by converſion fall under thee!</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:3"/>
            <p>Thou art the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh; is there any thing too hard for thee? When the Devil ſinn'd againſt thee (and thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Devil) thou didſt eaſily throw him out of heaven, and ſhackle him in chains of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and canſt thou not as eaſily throw him out of thoſe ſinners hearts which he has poſſeſſed and filled, and pull down all his ſtrong holds? And as for ſin, though it be ſo mighty a thing, that <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency was overcome by it, that Angels in Heaven could not ſtand before it; yet thou art able, and haſt promiſed to ſubdue it. Oh, ſhew thy power and Grace! Since thy mercy is ſo great, why ſhould there be ſo few partakers of mercy? Since thy Son is ſo able to ſave to the uttermoſt, why ſhould ſo ſmall a number be ſaved by him? Since the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> is ſo ſpacious, why ſhould Hell fill ſo exceeding faſt? Oh, let thy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial love be more generally manifeſted! Let thy healing and thy ſaving grace run in a much broader channel! Let thy tents be enlarged, and let them ſtretch forth the curtains of thine habitation! Let not ſo many ſouls be the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils prey, which are of greater value than the world; and which are capable of loving, and admiring, and glorifying thee for ever! An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, O my God, ſuch deſires as theſe, ſo far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> conſiſtent with the ſecrets of thy Counſel,
<pb facs="tcp:107824:4"/> and thy Wayes and Judgments, which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable and paſt finding out!</p>
            <p>Let thy Goſpel continue in this Land of <hi>England!</hi> Let the Sun of righteouſneſs ſhine forth in greater ſtrength and glory, and diſpel the miſts of error, and chaſe away the night of Ignorance! Let not the Sea be more full of water, than this Land of the knowledge of thy glory! As long as there is a Church on earth, let there be a Church in <hi>England!</hi> And let the Lamp of thy Word ſhine cleerly among us, as long as the Sun and the Moon ſhall ſhine in the Firmament!</p>
            <p>Thou who hast the hearts of all in thy own hand, incline ſome to read theſe following Sermons; and let all that read be the better by them. Let them underſtand in this their day the things which concern their peace! and obey thy Call to Turn, before thou comeſt to this Reſolution to call and cry no more after them! Oh, let none grow bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder by the light's ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their eyes! let none grow harder by the means which were deſign'd to ſoften them! Let not the Word of Life prove unto any a deadly ſavour! Let ſome ſouls date their converſion from their reading this Book; and let thoſe who are converted be further ſtrengthned by it. Encourage thy ſervant more and more, by
<pb facs="tcp:107824:4"/> making his labours more abundantly ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who has reſigned and given up himſelf to Thee; and whoſe greateſt H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nour and trueſt Happineſs it is to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine for ever, NATHANAEL VINCENT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:5"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS ſoon as thou haſt look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, immediately look off again, and look up to heaven!</p>
            <p>How canst thou ſee to read with any profit, unleſs the Father of lights do open thine eyes and give thee an underſtanding heart? He can ſhew thee wonders in the moſt commune Truths, which before thou wert unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
<pb facs="tcp:107824:6"/> with. Thoſe doctrines that are moſt uſually preached, as thy Judgment may yet more fully be informed about them; ſo I am ſure thy affections have need to be ſtirr'd up to bear ſome more proportionable ſuitableneſs unto the weight and concernment of them.</p>
            <p>It has moved my ſorrow, and almoſt my indignation, to ſee how many Truths, becauſe often (as 'tis needful) inſiſted on, are nauſeated by ſome Profeſſors. And yet alas theſe very Truths, though they have often heard them, they do not know them as they ought to know. As to any heart-affecting and operative knowledge, theſe perſons who fancy and conceit themſelves ſo very intelligent, are very groſly ignorant. Their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are ſtupid, and they were never brought under the power of the Word which is preached to them. Duties, though plainly and frequently preſſed are neglected, and ſins which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munly hear reproved, are yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding more communly given way to.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107824:6"/>
            <p>Thou who canſt not like of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe unleſs thy fancy be pleaſed, and thy itching ear clawed; what juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon haſt thou to queſtion, whether thy nature has been indeed renewed? for they who have been born again, deſire the ſincere milk of the word (though there be little mixture of what is hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane) that they may grow thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader!</hi> Art thou groſly ignorant and ungodly? How much then doth it concern thee to uſe thoſe means which are appointed for the attaining of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? Since without knowledge thy heart cannot be good; nor thou thy ſelf in a ſafe eſtate. Thou art gene aſtray; Oh, Turn immediately, leſt the next ſtep thou takest, be into the Grave and Hell! 'Tis but ſmall ſecurity not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thy danger; 'tis but a pitiful hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be ignorant of thy miſery, for this very ignorance increaſes thy dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and will make thy miſery the more unavoidable. Sin is ſuch a thing as none ever repented of their parting
<pb facs="tcp:107824:7"/> with; therefore be perſwaded to deny thy former ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and godly in this preſent evil world.</p>
            <p>If thou art a Profeſſor, but not a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſer of Religion; conſider, 'tis not a feigned converſion, but a turning with the whole heart, upon which Life is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and aſſured. If thou haſt a form of godlineſs without the power, what does this prove but that thou hast more of the Atheist in thee. Surely thou thinkeſt the Lord does not regard, and will not puniſh, at leaſt to thee he will be partial. I wonder how thou dareſt come ſo often into his preſence, ſo neer his Ark where his jealouſie is hotteſt, and ſo frequently engage in duties of his Worſhip; ſome ſin or vanity all the while keeping thy heart away from him.</p>
            <p>But if thou art indeed converted, Oh ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neerer unto God, and turn more and more like to him. Grace is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a thing, that methinks thou
<pb facs="tcp:107824:7"/> ſhouldſt be reſtleſly importunate for a greater meaſure of it. The more you follow on to know the Lord, the better you will love him, and the more unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you will be to leave him, and return again to folly.</p>
            <p>Converſion is a nail which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of old were hammering upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually. Our Lord and his Apoſtles en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to drive this nail home. And God of late has not only ſent his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to ply this buſineſs, but has taken the hammer of judgments to make this nail to enter. Now the ſtronger the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance is, we make, we muſt expect from this hammer the more ſtroaks. We have ſeen lately dayes of great calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and affliction, and yet they have in ſome ſenſe been alſo dayes of grace. Therefore temporal judgments have been ſent, that ſpiritual mercies might be prized, and eternal judgments might be prevented. God has had a deſign of love at the bottom of all his ſeverities. Let us comply with it; for if we ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:107824:8"/> walk contrary, he has threatned in fury to chaſtize us ſeven-fold more than as yet he has chaſtized us. And I may well tremble to think of thoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which will be ſeven times worſe than the Plague and Fire. But if we learn wiſdom and inſtruction by his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and turn unto him that has ſmitten us, we ſhall find the expreſsions of his favour and loving kindneſs, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> greater than ever were the ſigns of his diſpleaſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. V.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107824:8"/>
            <head>THE Converſion OF A SINNER:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EZEK. 33. 11. latter part.</bibl>
               <q>Turn ye, turn ye from your evil wayes; for why will ye die, O houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TIs not very eaſie to diſcern whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man diſcovered greater folly in <hi>departing</hi> from God at firſt, or whether his folly be now more inexcuſable in <hi>refuſing to return</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:107824:9"/> to him. <hi>At firſt</hi> he knew by bleſſed expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience how good it was to be neer his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, to enjoy the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the ſtate of innocency; and yet he ventur'd to go away. <hi>Now</hi> he feels the effects of his Apoſtacy; for ſin has load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with various miſeries, calamities, vexations, and yet how hardly is he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to come back again? The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men are eaſily induced to yield to Satan, as if 'twere their intereſt to give themſelves into the hands of a <hi>Murtherer;</hi> but the Lord beſides whom there is no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, may call, and call with frequency, with earneſtneſs, yet call in vain; their hearts are dull, their ears are deaf, they will not hearken to him. It can never be ſufficiently lamented, that ſin has made ſo many madmen in the world; <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death, bleſſing</hi> and <hi>curſing</hi> are ſet before them; yet death is choſen before life, the moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhing and intollerable curſes are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, when bleſſings of the higheſt, and moſt durable nature, are rejected.</p>
            <q>Proh ſuperi! quantum mortalia pect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra caecae Noctis habent!</q>
            <p>Hence 'tis that the Lord expoſtulates
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107824:9"/> not only in reference to <hi>ſin,</hi> but in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>puniſhment:</hi> He not only ſayes, <hi>Why will you venture to tranſgreſs;</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>Why are you ſo forward to die, O houſe of</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>The Prophet in the beginning of this Chapter, is by the Lord appointed a <hi>Watchman</hi> over the houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> he is commanded to lift up his voice, when he ſees the revenging ſword drawn forth, and comming to cut the ungodly off for their ungodlineſs; and unleſs he call to the wicked to turn and live, he is acceſſary to their death, and their blood will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at his hand. And being thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned, he is commanded to ſtop the mouths of evil doers, who cavil and reply againſt their Maker, and charge God fooliſhly.</p>
            <p>A Controverſie it ſeems there was, at whoſe door the deſtruction of ſinners is to be laid: The houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily and boldly lay the blame on God; they ſtick not to ſay, the way of the Lord is not equal. But the God of mercy, and of truth, does vindicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from that undeſerved imputation; profeſſing, that if ſinners were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly bent upon their own ruin, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107824:10"/> would be eſcaped. By his life he ſwears, that the death of the wicked pleaſes him not; therefore in the Text his voice is loud and doubled, <hi>Turn ye, turn ye, from your evil wayes;</hi> and the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle is ſet upon the right horſe, mens own <hi>Wills</hi> are the cauſe of their own <hi>Woe. Why will ye die, O houſe of</hi> Iſrael?</p>
            <p>The words expreſs a very pathetical and ſerious call, wherein obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The perſons called, <hi>The houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To what they are called; they are called <hi>to Turn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The urgency of this call, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the doubling of it, <hi>Turn ye, turn ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. From what they muſt turn, <hi>from their evil wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The argument uſed to prevail, which has abundance of holy rhetorick in it; <hi>VVhy will ye die?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Without turning death is certain. Satan may ſay to the poſterity, as once to the Parents, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely die;</hi> but this will be ſound true, <hi>Thoſe ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e turned into Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Pſal. 9. 17. who will not turn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to God; thither 'tis that evil wayes have all a tendency. Several paths there are in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107824:10"/> broad way, but in <hi>death,</hi> the <hi>ſecond death,</hi> they all conclude and meet. Therefore the Lord is brought in, pitying of ſinners, and pleading with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhy will ye die? Is it becauſe I am ſpeedy in revenging? you know I am ſlow to anger; and by experience have found me ſo, elſe my wrath had long e're this broken forth upon you; or is it becauſe I am inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not to be intreated when once provoked? VVhy, I have proclaim'd myſelf ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and plenteous in mercy, unto all that call upon him. Or is it becauſe you never heard of the way and means of recovering life, and flying from the puniſhment you have deſerved? How often have I ſent my Prophets, that you might be brought to believe, to repent, and to obey? But ſtill your neck is as an iron ſinew; you are reſolved to ruſh on in ſin. If you pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, you may</hi> thank your ſelves. <hi>If you are deſtroyed, 'tis becauſe you</hi> chuſe deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Three Doctrines the Text affords us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That evil wayes are the wayes of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The great reaſon why men die, and die for ever, is becauſe they will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The Lord does call and call a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain upon ſinners to turn from their evil wayes and live.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107824:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. I begin with the firſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>That evil wayes are the wayes of death.</hi> As they are <hi>morally evil;</hi> ſo <hi>evil and deſtructive</hi> to them that walk in them. Indeed theſe wayes may ſeem right, but becauſe of this, they are not the leſs, but the more pernicious, <hi>Prov. 14. 12. There is a way that ſeemeth right unto a man; but the end thereof are the wayes of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Theſe evil wayes do many times accele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and haſten death temporal.</hi> That was the ſentence pronounced upon mans fall; <hi>Duſt thou art, and unto duſt thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</hi> And how often by ſin is the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that ſentence ſpeeded? We read of ſome not ſuffered <hi>to live out half their dayes,</hi> Pſal. 55. 23. the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they live ſo wickedly. Thoſe whoſe carcaſſes fell in the wilderneſs, might have lived to poſſeſs the Land of Promiſe; but they ſometimes <hi>murmured,</hi> ſometimes they <hi>commit idolatry,</hi> ſometimes <hi>fornication;</hi> and at laſt, the <hi>oath is ſworn they ſhould not enter into Canaan.</hi> The intemperate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, how do they waſte their ſtrength? How many diſeaſes do they puniſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with? And though ſo <hi>miſerably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared for judgment,</hi> haſten their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this world to the tribunal of him, <hi>who judges righteouſly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107824:11"/>2. <hi>Theſe evil wayes; God who is our life is not to be found in:</hi> In a <hi>ſpiritual ſenſe</hi> we are <hi>dead though alive,</hi> while we walk here. The <hi>Epheſians</hi> are ſaid <hi>to be dead in treſpaſſes and ſin, while they walked according to the courſe of this world, and had their converſation in the luſts of their fleſh,</hi> Eph. 2. 2, 3. If the life of the ſoul does conſiſt in being <hi>united to God,</hi> in being <hi>anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted and acted by his Spirit;</hi> then iniquity that ſeparates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 2. muſt needs be <hi>granted a deadly thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Theſe evil wayes are the beaten path to hells damnation, to that death which is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi> Never any came to hell but through theſe wayes; and there is not one that continues to walk in them without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, but ſhall at laſt come thither. The enemy upon the pale horſe without a ſecond is deadful; but when Hell follows immediately after him; alas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what hand can be ſtrong? what heart can be able to endure? This <hi>ſecond Death</hi> is by one of the Fathers called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The death that is immortal;</hi> becauſe the ſinner is never put out of his pain, alwayes tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured, but never quite diſpatched; the fire burns ſtill, but never totally conſumes them whom it burns; the worm ſtill gnaws, but is never ſatisfied.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107824:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhither away beſotted and blinded ſoul? whither is it thou art making ſuch poſt haſte? Is it gain, delight, and happineſs which thou haſt in chaſe, that thou ſeemeſt rather to flie than run towards it? Alas no; 'tis in the broad way that thou driveſt on ſo furiouſly; 'tis not gain, but loſs; 'tis not pleaſure, but pain; 'tis not an happineſs, but miſery; ay, and the extreameſt miſery which thou art purſuing. Oh ſtop thy courſe and go no further! Oh leave this lower path, Prov. 15. 24. The way of life is above to the wiſe, that he may depart from hell b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee in what reſpects evil wayes are the wayes of death. Now, <hi>the righteouſneſs of God, in puniſhing thoſe with death</hi> that perſiſt in theſe wayes, will be evident, if theſe things following are conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Theſe wayes are expreſly forbidden by him that is the ſupream Law-giver; who has power to ſave, and to deſtroy;</hi> and for ſo <hi>mean a wretch</hi> as <hi>man</hi> is, to affront and deſpiſe, that <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> that is ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely high above him,</hi> does juſtly deſerve an <hi>infinite puniſhment.</hi> Beſides, the Lord profers himſelf to a ſinner, if he will forſake his evil wayes and thoughts: Now if the ſinner reject that offer, and prefer not only the <hi>empty world,</hi> but the <hi>vileſt luſts</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107824:12"/> before the <hi>bleſſed God,</hi> let <hi>reaſon</hi> judge if it be not <hi>juſt,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>eternally be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from him.</hi> And this <hi>poena damni,</hi> loſs of God, is moſt properly the death ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, 'tis indeed the very Hell of Hell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sinners are threatned with death;</hi> if therefore they will venture upon that which brings them under the laſh of the threatnings, 'tis but juſt they ſhould ſmart for that preſumption: They are <hi>forewarned to flee from that wrath which is to come;</hi> but if they take no warning, that wrath will very juſtly overtake them. They cannot plead, either that they knew not their Maſters will; or that they were ignorant of the penalty following upon their rebelling againſt it. How often have thoſe that enjoy the light of the Goſpel, been informed that 'tis the will of God they ſhould ſorrow and rend their hearts for ſin; that 'tis the will of God they ſhould believe in his Son; that 'tis the will of God even their ſanctification, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. Nay, how often have they been foretold of the many ſtripes that muſt be endured by thoſe that continue in wilful diſobedience? 'Tis not unequal then, ſince they made the Lord a lyar by their unbelief, that he ſhould vindicate his
<pb facs="tcp:107824:13"/> truth, and cauſe them to <hi>feel</hi> thoſe plagues and torments which thouſands of times they were warned of; but had no <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>fear</hi> concerning them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As ſinners are threatned becauſe of their evil wayes, <hi>ſo they are ſhewed which is the way of life and peace, and very much preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to walk in it.</hi> Aſſiſting and ſtrengthning grace is profered to them; but if neither that glory and immortality at the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi> of the way, nor that help and grace which they may have <hi>in</hi> the way, are regarded; but the <hi>paths of deſtruction and miſery</hi> (as they are called) <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 16. are preferred; they themſelves indeed do <hi>wrong</hi> their own ſouls; but God is <hi>righteous</hi> in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them.</p>
            <p>The only uſe I ſhall make of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is to <hi>caution you againſt theſe evil wayes, that are the wayes of death.</hi> You that have through grace left them, take heed of declining towards them. It has coſt the Saints dear, when they have ſtept aſide; their falls have defiled them and broken their bones. And you that ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to walk in theſe wayes, at laſt open your eyes, and ſee whither you are going. Upon the <hi>reading theſe lines,</hi> make a ſtop without delay, <hi>leſt ſudden death, ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb facs="tcp:107824:13"/> ſudden damnation</hi> come upon you, and there be no poſſibility of eſcaping, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Let not the profit of theſe wayes blind you.</hi> Riches are deceitful, they appear what they are not, and while we are eagerly purſuing theſe, we are gulled and cheated of far truer riches; we miſs of that <hi>treaſure in heaven that will never fail, Luk.</hi> 12. 33. Be not deluded by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon; ſatisfaction, eaſe, contentment may be promiſed; but you will be paid in trouble and vexation. Riches are likened by our Lord to <hi>Thorns,</hi> partly becauſe they <hi>cho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> the good ſeed of the Word, and partly becauſe they <hi>pierce</hi> thoſe that do at upon them with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorrows. Take the <hi>ballances</hi> of the ſanctuary, and <hi>weigh</hi> the gain that you get by walking in your evil wayes, with the loſs that you both do and will ſuſtain; and then 'twill be apparent, that Satan's and the heart's plea of profit is very unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. You gain <hi>earth,</hi> but you loſe <hi>grace;</hi> you gain <hi>gold,</hi> but you loſe <hi>God;</hi> you gain a <hi>little</hi> of the world, which you can keep but a <hi>very little while,</hi> but you loſe <hi>your ſouls,</hi> and an <hi>whole eternity of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Let n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the pleaſure of theſe evil wayes
<pb facs="tcp:107824:14"/> enſnare you;</hi> the pleaſures of ſin uſually delight only the more bruitiſh part of man; and how much does one that has a reaſonable ſoul act below himſelf, in minding thoſe pleaſures that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune even to the beaſts themſelves? <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> had an abundance of them, <hi>Whatever his eyes deſired he kept not from them, neither with-held he from his heart any joy;</hi> but he found them ſo mean, ſo low, ſo unſuitable, that in the midſt of them he cryes out, <hi>All is vanity and vaxation of ſpirit,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 10, 11. <hi>Pleaſures</hi> are <hi>delightful dreams,</hi> but how <hi>ſhort</hi> are they, how ſoon does <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, death,</hi> if not <hi>Hell</hi> awaken us? They that are lovers of pleaſures more than lovers of God, how inconſiderate are they what they chuſe, or what they refuſe? <hi>Pleaſures</hi> are the <hi>baits</hi> which cover ſin, and make it ſwallowed down with eagerneſs; they are the <hi>fatal potion</hi> which <hi>ſtupifie:</hi> the ſoul, and makes it lye <hi>ſenceleſs and helpleſs</hi> in <hi>extream danger;</hi> they are the <hi>finer,</hi> and yet <hi>moſt ſtrong cords,</hi> whereby Satan <hi>draws</hi> men down to the <hi>chambers of death;</hi> nay, they are the <hi>fewel</hi> that <hi>heat</hi> the burning lake, <hi>Rev. 18. 7. By how much ſhe hath glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified her ſelf and lived deliciouſly, ſo much torment and ſorrow give her.</hi> Oh, how will
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107824:14"/> the voluptuous one day ſmart for all their pleaſures!</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Let not the multitude of thoſe who walk in theſe evil wayes confirm and harden you. Lot</hi> walked <hi>alone</hi> in the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, though <hi>Sod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> was <hi>generally</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed by an ungodly converſation; he would not follow a <hi>multitude to do evil.</hi> He that ſaid, <hi>Strait is the gate and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it,</hi> Mat. 7. ſurely never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his Diſciples ſhould go in the <hi>beaten path</hi> of the <hi>world.</hi> Sinner, deceive not thy ſelf with this, <hi>Thou doſt what others do,</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt ſhift as well as they.</hi> Thou and they will <hi>fare alike</hi> indeed; that is, be turned into hell for your wickedneſs. 'Twill be no comfort <hi>there</hi> to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in thy miſery; but rather among the damned, there will be a <hi>torturing grief</hi> and <hi>indignation</hi> at the ſight one of another, to conſider what <hi>incarnate devils</hi> they were to one anothers ſouls, and helped for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one anothers condemnation. Upon this ſcore it might be that the rich man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. was ſo <hi>unwilling his brethren ſhould come to the place of torment,</hi> becauſe if damned for thoſe ſins which he in his life<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>time had been acceſſary to; their company
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107824:15"/> with him in Hell would have but added to his woe. We uſe to ſay here, <hi>The more, the merrier;</hi> but there 'twill be, <hi>The more, the ſadder.</hi> When God has <hi>all his enemies</hi> in one place together, and none of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mingled with them, then <hi>all his wrath</hi> will be ſtirred up, and all the vials of his fury poured down upon them. I have done with that firſt Doctrine, <hi>That evil wayes are the wayes of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. The ſecond Doctrine is this: <hi>The great reaſon why men die &amp; die for ever, is becauſe they will.</hi> They will be the ſervants of ſin, though death be all the wages they ſhall certainly have for all their toylſom and laborious ſervice. Sinners will not be purged, <hi>Jer. 13. ult. Wo unto thee, O</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>wilt thou not be made clean? when ſhall it once be?</hi> They will not be gathered under the wing of Chriſt, though <hi>there</hi> only be the <hi>place of refuge,</hi> both from the <hi>rage of Satan,</hi> and from <hi>the wrath of God, Mat. 23. 37. O Jeruſalem! Jeruſalem! thou that killeſt the Prophets and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, as an Hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her brood under her wings, and ye would n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t?</hi> Nay, the <hi>wills</hi> of many, who have often ſlighted the admonitions and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107824:15"/> calls of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, are ſo deſperately bent to ſin, that though them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>flames</hi> and <hi>torments</hi> it makes others ſuffer; yet they <hi>would</hi> not be perſwaded to forſake it, <hi>Luk. 16. 30, 31. Nay, Father</hi> Abraham, <hi>but if one went to them from the dead they will repent; and he ſaid unto him, If they hear not</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets; neither</hi> will <hi>they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, though one roſe from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My work in the opening of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, will be <hi>firſt</hi> to demonſtrate the truth of it, <hi>That men die becauſe they will. Secondly,</hi> to evidence <hi>that mens inability to what is good, ſo often ſpoken of in Scripture, does not at all contradict this doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Arguments to demonſtrate that mens own wills are the great cauſe of their death and perdition, are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One Argument ſhall be drawn from <hi>the natural corruption and depravation of the will of man.</hi> And wherein does this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption lye, but in the <hi>wills declining from God,</hi> the fountain of life and peace, and <hi>inclining to what is evil?</hi> Though the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (wo unto him) <hi>does call that evil good;</hi> and imagins that to be <hi>ſweet,</hi> which will prove as <hi>bitter</hi> and poyſonous as the <hi>very gall of aſps</hi> unto him. <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agians</hi> may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107824:16"/> liken the will of man unto a <hi>pure Virgin,</hi> which in the firſt Apoſtacy did eſcape <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flouring;</hi> but certain it is, both from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and experience, that in the <hi>will, ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal ſin</hi> does moſt of all ſhew it ſelf. He that does not underſtand <hi>his heart to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately wicked,</hi> Jer. 17. 9. 'Tis a ſign his heart deceives him, and with his heart he is utterly unacquainted. What unbelief, what pride, what alienation from the life of God, what enmity againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which is holy, juſt, and good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. is there in the will of a natural man? The will then being ſo deeply corrupted, and bearing ſuch ſway as indeed it does, muſt needs hinder converſion to God, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, which it ſo much diſlikes; and conſequently have a great hand in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the children of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Argument ſhall be drawn <hi>from the juſtneſs of God's reproofs and anger.</hi> Certainly he would not ſo ſharply repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them; his anger would not ſo ſmoak againſt them, becauſe of their ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wilfulneſs in their evil wayes, if they had a <hi>ſincere will,</hi> and only wanted <hi>power</hi> to do that which is good. When the Lord inflicted judgments upon his ancient people, he ſpeaks of their <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107824:16"/> 
               <hi>refuſing</hi> to hearken, and to be reclaimed; and this he does to vindicate the equity of his ſeverer wayes of dealing with them. We read, 2 <hi>King. 17. 13, 14, 18. That the Lord teſtified againſt</hi> Iſrael <hi>by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Seers, ſaying, Turn ye from your evil wayes, and keep my commandements. Notwithſtanding they</hi> would not <hi>hear, but</hi> hardned <hi>their necks like unto the neck of their fathers, which did not believe in the Lord their God;</hi> now upon this <hi>wilfulneſs</hi> followed, and that very juſtly, <hi>God's anger</hi> and <hi>their deſtruction. Therefore the Lord was very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with the children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and removed them out of his ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, I am to prove, That <hi>mens inability</hi> to do that which is good, does <hi>not thwart</hi> this Doctrine, that their ſin and miſery is to be laid at their wills door. The Holy Ghoſt that he might <hi>humble</hi> the children of men, and be at down the <hi>opinion</hi> they have of their <hi>own power</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> and make them uſe that ſpeech of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa. 45. 25. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Lord have I righteouſneſs and ſtrength,</hi> does inculcate this, that man in his ſinful &amp; degenerate ſtate is unable to that which is ſpiritually good; therefore we are ſaid to be <hi>without ſtrength,</hi> Rom. 5. 6.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107824:17"/> 
               <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 5. <hi>We are ſaid to be faint, and to have no might,</hi> Iſa. 40. 29. And our Lord tells us plainly, <hi>Joh. 15. 5. Without me ye can do nothing.</hi> But for all this, though we want a <hi>power</hi> to do good, our <hi>wills</hi> are to be <hi>blamed</hi> for the <hi>evil</hi> which is done by us. It muſt not be imagined that the Scripture mentions ſinners <hi>inability to do good,</hi> to put <hi>an excuſe</hi> into their mouths, for their doing of evil; but to drive them to Chriſt, who <hi>can ſtrengthen them to do all things,</hi> Phil. 4. 13. 'Tis true, man is <hi>una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> but withal he is <hi>unwilling</hi> to do what God requires of him, though tending to his own welfare. The reaſon why he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in ſin, and is undone by it, is not <hi>only becauſe he cannot convert himſelf,</hi> but alſo, and that <hi>principally,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be converted.</hi> This will be made further to appear in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sinful man <hi>imagines</hi> himſelf <hi>able</hi> to turn from his evil wayes; he defers his repentance, as if he could <hi>turn to God at an hours warning:</hi> Now that he <hi>does not,</hi> what he <hi>thinks he can;</hi> his <hi>own will</hi> muſt be the impediment, and this he muſt blame, if ſo be he periſhes.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:107824:17"/>2. Sinful man <hi>will not do what he is really able to perform; one talent</hi> he has, but he will not trade with it; many ſins that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to wrath and vengeance, he might abſtain from, if he would; but alas! he is voluntarily a ſlave to them, and is pleaſed with this ſervitude. The Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer <hi>wilfully</hi> goes to the Harlots houſe, the unrighteous worldling wilfully gets diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt gain; therefore it follows, that theſe wilfully deſtroy themſelves. A natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man can do that which is good, as to the matter, though he fail in the manner of doing: He can pray, hear, read; but he wilfully omits theſe duties; and ſo wilfully ſubjects himſelf to the curſe that's threatned upon his omiſſion. He will not do what he really can; and then ſurely if his power were enlarged, it would not be uſed. He that can well ſpare it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to give a penny to the poor, we may conclude, that though he could ſpare it, he would be unwilling to give a pound: In like manner a natural man, who will not do what he can to be ſaved, which is but little, were his power greater, he would not do more in order to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>3. Sinful man is <hi>ſorry that he is able to do
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107824:18"/> ſo much,</hi> he <hi>wiſhes</hi> that he were <hi>totally impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> that ſo it might ſerve as an <hi>excuſe</hi> for him. This ſhews the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of his <hi>will.</hi> Further, he will not uſe the means by which grace and ſtrength from heaven are conveyed; he will not wait and call on God, he will not ſeek unto him for the accompliſhing of the promiſes made in the gracious Covenant. Nay, he wilfully reſiſts the Spirit when he comes to work upon him; he had rather be let alone in ſin. That's the language of ungodly ones, <hi>Job 21. 14. They ſay unto God, depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy ways.</hi> The wicked man, though he may cavil that he wants <hi>power,</hi> yet his <hi>want of will</hi> to be turned and live, is that which mainly ruins him. And all thoſe <hi>high thoughts</hi> and <hi>reaſonings</hi> againſt God, as if he were an <hi>hard Maſter,</hi> as if <hi>his wayes were not equal,</hi> at the <hi>great day,</hi> how will he be aſhame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them? When conſcience ſhall flie in his face, and in good ſadneſs reproach him with this; He was often warned and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon, but <hi>would</hi> not turn that he migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave life.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The Application follows.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. Of Information in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107824:18"/>1. Do men die for ever becauſe they will? <hi>Then who art thou, O man, that chargeſt God with thy deſtruction?</hi> Surely herein thou chargeſt God fooliſhly; as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights not in thy ſin, ſo neither in thy death. The malefactor muſt not be angry with the Judge for paſſing a ſentence of condemnation upon him, but he ought to blame himſelf for doing that for which he deſerves to be condemned. <hi>How often has the Lord called but you have refuſed, how often has he ſtretched forth his hand, all the day long, but all the day long you have been diſobedient and gainſaying?</hi> Rom. 10. <hi>ult.</hi> How ſpeechleſs will this make you, when he comes to judge the world in righteouſneſs?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do men die for ever becauſe they will? <hi>Then the death of the wicked is moſt juſt and righteous.</hi> 'Tis but equal that the willing ſlaves of ſin, that would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Lords freemen, ſhould be fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in chains of darkneſs. The offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor that refuſes a pardon offered, juſtly, nay, doubly deſerves to have judgment ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, both becauſe of <hi>his offence,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>ſlights mercy.</hi> The Patient who thruſts away the Phyſician, who would heal him of a ſore diſtemper, very well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107824:19"/> ſerves to die for it; and the ſinner who will not turn to God, who rejects the Lord Jeſus, who is able both to pardon and to heal him; though he periſh and be <hi>condemned,</hi> yet he is not in the leaſt <hi>wronged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Do men die for ever becauſe they will? <hi>What a torture will it be to them in Hell, to think it was their own wilfulneſs which brought them thither.</hi> Such kind of reflections as theſe will be as ſo many poyſoned daggers to pierce the very ſoul of a damned reprobate. <hi>What ailed me to prove a devil to my ſelf! what ailed me to ſide with Satan, for the bringing about my own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction! what phrenzy was this, to make the whips my ſelf, wherewithal I am to be laſhed! to kindle the flames with my own hands; in which I muſt dwell and burn for ever!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Shall be of Caution: <hi>Take heed of wilful ſinning, which is the high road leading to death. Take heed alſo leſt you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelves with a ſeeming willingneſs to eſcape deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Let me caution you againſt wilful ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> The more of the will is in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, the more of provocation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> is ſo earneſt <hi>to be kept from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſins which he knew, becauſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107824:19"/> to be ſo great,</hi> Pſal. 19. 13. In a Land and time of light, take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wilfully ignorant: In the midſt of helps and encouragements to duty, take heed of ſloth, which is a fault of the will; but <hi>be a follower of them who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes,</hi> Heb. 6. 12. Let no ſin be loved, pleaded for, lived in; let not the <hi>pleaſing taſte</hi> make thee venture upon any <hi>forbidden fruit;</hi> let not the fine-coloured skin make thee to hug any Serpent in thy boſom, which will ſting thee to death.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let me caution you againſt <hi>that which is only a ſeeming willingneſs to turn from ſin, and eſcape deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>An idle uninduſtrious will, is only a ſeeming will.</hi> A lazy wiſh to be ſaved, where there is no ſerious uſing of the means of ſalvation, ſignifies nothing, but that you are groſly ignorant and ſtupid, ignorant of the worth of ſalvation, and ſtupidly unſenſible of your own danger.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A will for the future is only a ſeeming will.</hi> Moſt of them who go on in their evil wayes, have a will to leave them hereafter; but this only ſhews their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unwillingneſs. And if you are back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to turn now, you are likely hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107824:20"/> to be more averſe. When God is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther departed from you, when Satan has built ſtronger holds in you, when conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is grown more ſtupid, when cuſtom in ſin has doubled the ſtrength and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence of your natural inclination to it. Alas! how many millions have died and been taken away in their iniquities, that were as fully reſolved upon repenting hereafter, as any that are now alive? Take heed of this <hi>rock,</hi> upon which ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have <hi>ſplit,</hi> and been <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt away for ever.</hi> God's will is for the preſent; he ſayes, <hi>To day if you will hear my voice, harden not your hearts,</hi> Heb. 3. 7, 8. But if now when God is willing to give you life, you are unwilling; he may be hereafter unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, when you would fain have it: <hi>When death and deſtruction come upon you as a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind,</hi> he has threatned <hi>that you ſhall call upon him</hi> for life and ſalvation, but it ſhall be far from you; <hi>you ſhall ſeek him early, but you ſhall not find him, if now you hate knowledge, and do not chuſe the fear of the Lord,</hi> Prov. 1. 28, 29.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>A will upon a miſtake is only a ſeeming will.</hi> Thoſe whom our Lord likens to the ſtony ground, heard the word with joy, and were willing to embrace it, but they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107824:20"/> dreamt not of the croſs and perſecution; <hi>that</hi> made them to fall away. Many ſeem willing to be Converts, but <hi>they ſit not down</hi> and <hi>count the coſt of converſion:</hi> And when once they are informed, that they muſt deny themſelves, let go all out of their affections preſently, and out of their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion too, when ſtanding in competition with the Lord Jeſus; when they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that a bill of divorce muſt be given to their <hi>Herodias,</hi> that they muſt bid defiance to every luſt, though it plead ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much delight or gain that it may ſtill be embraced; when they are inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they muſt watch, and pray, and walk with the greateſt care, and fervency, and circumſpection, that they muſt take the Kingdom of heaven with an holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as it were by ſtorm, elſe they will fall ſhort and loſe the crown. Oh then they cry out, <hi>Theſe are hard ſayings; who can hear them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 3. Of Exhortation. Since men die becauſe they will, Let me perſwade you to <hi>conſent that your wills may be renewed.</hi> Man has not a <hi>worſe enemy</hi> than his <hi>own will,</hi> until there be a change wrought in it. And that this change may be effected, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe directions.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:107824:21"/>1. <hi>Judge your ſelves becauſe of your natural perverſneſs;</hi> till ſenſible of this you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in a right manner humbled. That thou haſt ſinned ſo much, ſo long, ſhould very much affect and afflict thee before God; but that thou haſt a will to ſin ten thouſand times more, were it not for the reſtraints of grace; nay, to ſin unto eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh, what confuſion and ſorrow ſhould this cauſe!</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Study the deceitfulneſs of the Tempter and the VVorld;</hi> then your hearts will not be ſo forward to be taken with their baits, and to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rawn away from God. The world is vain and vexing, and Satan is a lyar and a murderer, you have little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to yield to either.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Set before your eyes the bleſſedneſs of life eternal, and the miſery of everlaſting death,</hi> that life may be choſen, and the way to it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Be fervent in prayer, that the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe would give you a new heart, and work in you to will of his own good pleaſure,</hi> Ezek. 36. 26. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 13. And if he cauſe your hearts to deſire grace and glory, he will ſatisfie thoſe deſires he has raiſed in you; if he work in you to will and to do, notwithſtanding all oppoſition,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107824:21"/> you <hi>ſhall work out your own ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>an abundant entrance ſhall be adminiſtred to you, into the everlaſting kingdom.</hi> Thus of the ſecond Doctrine. <hi>The reaſon why men die, and die for ever, is becauſe they will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. The third Doctrine follows. <hi>The Lord does call and call again upon ſinners to turn from their evil wayes and live. Turn ye, Turn ye,</hi> ſaith God in the Text. The buſineſs of Converſion is not a thing which man firſt thought of; nay, he would never think of it, or be perſwaded to it, if the Lord did not call after him, and make that call effectual. We read indeed in Scripture of ſenſible and awakened pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, crying and begging to be turned; but theſe <hi>cryes</hi> are but as it were the <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho's</hi> of God's voice and call that went before. In the handling of the Doctrine, I ſhall, Firſt, ſhew <hi>how God calls upon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to turn to him.</hi> Secondly, <hi>VVhy he does it.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Explain the nature of this Converſion or turning.</hi> Fourthly, conclude with Application.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, I am to ſhew, <hi>How God calls upon ſinners to turn to him.</hi> This he does ſeveral wayes.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>He calls upon them from Mount Ebal.</hi> That was the Mount from whence the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107824:22"/> curſes were denounced; he tells them in his Word of the curſedneſs and wo of the unconverted's ſtate. He ſends the Law as <hi>School-Maſter</hi> to teach them a ſad Leſſon; that becauſe of their frequent tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they are juſt upon the brink of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal miſery; and his deſign is, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be awakened and ſtopt in their deſtructive way, and <hi>not flatter</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>with hopes of peace,</hi> though they ſtill walk on after the <hi>imagination of their evil heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This voice of the Lord by the Law is loud and terrible, uttered on purpoſe to rouze &amp; ſtartle them that are dead aſleep. When the Law was delivered, <hi>There was a burning with fire, there was blackneſs, and darkneſs, and tempeſt, the ſound of a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and the voice of words, which voice they that heard, increated that the word might not be ſpoken to them any more; and ſo terrible was the ſight, that</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid, I exceedingly fear and quake,</hi> Heb. 12. 18, 19, 21. And if the manner of the Law's delivery was ſo dreadful, much more dreadful will be the manner of the Laws execution upon thoſe by whom it has been violated? The <hi>fire and darkneſs</hi> at <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> were nothing in compariſon with <hi>the fire of Hell,</hi> and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107824:22"/> 
                  <hi>blackneſs of darkneſs there.</hi> Upon the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitently wicked the Lord has threatned <hi>to rain ſnares, fire and brimſton, and an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible tempeſt, this ſhall be the portion of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p, Pſal.</hi> 11. 6. And truly this lecture of the Law is neceſſary, that we may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to a true knowledge and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſin; and when we have been thus at the foot of Mount <hi>Ebal</hi> and <hi>Sinai,</hi> and have heard that ſin is the great hindrance of all ſorts of bleſſings, and loads us with curſes of all ſorts, both temporal and ſpiritual, and alſo everlaſting; this is the way to cure our unreaſonable doating upon it, and to make us fear and tremble becauſe we have given ſo much way to it.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>God calls upon ſinners from Mount Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizzim,</hi> to turn to him; from hence of old the bleſſings were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ounded forth. He not only gives them a ſight of <hi>wrath, as nigh at hand,</hi> while they continue work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of iniquity; but alſo he gives them a view of <hi>mercy afar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff,</hi> which ſhall be <hi>brought neer them</hi> on condition their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is forſaken. <hi>Upon the unrighteous man's forſaking of his ſinful ways and thoughts, mercy and abundant pardon are promiſed,</hi> Iſa. 55. 7. This call of the Goſpel from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107824:23"/> Mount <hi>Gerizzim,</hi> is like the <hi>ſtill voice</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>ſtrong wind, the fire and the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</hi> How full of encouragement are thoſe words, <hi>Zech. 1. 3. Turn unto me, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and I will turn unto you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And <hi>Hoſ. 14. 1. O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>return unto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt fallen by thy iniquity. Thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thy ſelf, but in me is thy help found. I will heal thy back-ſlidings, and will love thee freely,</hi> though thou deſerveſt nothing but my anger and my hatred.</p>
               <p>Satan, by tempting us to ſin, has taken away our bleſſing from us, yet we ought not to deſpond; for the Lord has <hi>more than one bleſſing.</hi> That which the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> forfeited, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was ſent to reſtore, <hi>Act. 3. 26. God having raiſed up his Son Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you in turning away every one of you from his iniquities.</hi> The Lord does take ſinners up, as it were, into mout <hi>Gerizzim;</hi> he ſhews them his Kingdom, and the glories of it; he tells them of his ſtore of bleſſings, of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable benefits which his Son has pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, juſtification, adoption, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, glory; and aſſures them, <hi>All ſhall be theirs,</hi> if they will but turn indeed. And truly theſe are other kind of offers,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107824:23"/> than Satan ever did, or can poſſibly make.</p>
               <p>3. God calls upon ſinners to turn, <hi>by the moſt paſſionate pleadings and preſſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulations.</hi> His deſign in expoſtulating, is to make them ſenſible of their <hi>unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs</hi> in perſuing deceitful vanities, and fulfilling their defiling luſts, and refuſing to convert unto him, who both can ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie them from their defilements, and ſatisfie them with his all-ſufficiency. He expoſtulates the matter with <hi>Judah,</hi> Iſa. 55. 2, 3. <hi>Why will you ſpend your money, for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which cannot ſatisfie? ſince upon your coming to me, the life of your ſouls, and the ſure mercies of an everlaſting covenant may be obtained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord pleads with the ungodly by the Miniſtry of the Word, after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>What! Though you are told of ſins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, defiling and damnable nature; will you ſtill embrace and hold it faſt, to my</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour <hi>and your own</hi> deſtruction? <hi>Though you are forewarned of the heat and heavineſs of my anger, will you not flee from it? though you are informed ſo often how little Hell will be for your eaſe, will you needs run thither, and burn there for ever? though you are told of a Kingdom that cannot be moved, will not you
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107824:24"/> be moved with deſire after it, will you not be perſwaded to ſtrive for it? Are grace and glory of no worth at all? Is not a Saviour to be prized by them, who by ſin have enſlaved and loſt themſelves, and are in danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt unto eternity? Conſider theſe things, and ſhew your ſelves</hi> men, O ye tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. Thus the Lord pleads, that he may prevail with ſinners, for their own good.</p>
               <p>4. God calls upon ſinners to turn, <hi>by the examples of others, and by the voice of the rod upon themſelves.</hi> The ungodly are very prone to obſerve bad examples, that they may imitate them; but 'tis their duty to take notice when exemplary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are inflicted upon them, that they may be afraid to follow them in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs any longer. When we behold others plagued for the ſins which we are guilty of, the Lord bids us to ſee the heinouſneſs of our own iniquities, in the ſtroaks which others have felt before our eyes. And we may juſtly expect, that like ſins will have like ends, if there be a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in provocation. Examples are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purpoſely ſet before us, <hi>that we may not luſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after evil things,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 6. that we may be <hi>admoniſhed</hi> to turn out of <hi>thoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107824:24"/> paths,</hi> which have <hi>led others to ruin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>eſpecially</hi> when the rod does fall upon our own backs, God calls upon us in a more perceivable and ſenſible way to turn to him: The deſign of the rod is to <hi>imbitter</hi> ſin, both to the <hi>fleſh</hi> and to the <hi>conſcience;</hi> and that it may not any longer be imagined delightful, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing cauſe of every ſtripe that is endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The <hi>rod has a voice</hi> as well as the Word, which 'tis <hi>our wiſdom to hear:</hi> When affliction is laid upon the ſinners <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyns, by it the Lord ſpeaks ſuch kind of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anguage, <hi>Jer. 2. 17. Haſt thou not procured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his unto thy ſelf by ſin? to turn from thine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niquity is to conſult thine own eaſe; let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain of the rod (which yet is nothing to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ains of Hell) convince thee, that ſin is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be admired for its pleaſure; at preſent thou art only chaſtized with whips, but if thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncorrigible, and ſinneſt yet more and more, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly at laſt thou ſhalt be laſhed with ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. God calls upon ſinners to turn to him, <hi>by the internal voice and motions of his Spirit.</hi> The Spirit often ſuggeſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſinful and falſe way. <hi>This is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot the way, and therefore turn out of it;</hi> but concerning the way of holineſs, which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107824:25"/> leads to God. <hi>This is the way,</hi> therefore <hi>turn into it,</hi> and without declining <hi>walk i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it,</hi> Iſa. 30. 21. All the <hi>other Calls</hi> will be to <hi>little purpoſe,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Spirit do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them.</hi> Without his conviction, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> denunciation of curſes will not awaken Without his illumination, the bleſſing profered will be undervalued. Withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his ſetting an edge upon them, the moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pathetical expoſtulations will not hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the leaſt efficacy to perſwade; the loude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> word will be no more regarded, than if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were a whiſper. Unleſs the Spirit joy his teaching and inſtruction, the rod wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be mute and inſignificant; nothing wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be learned either by perſonal affliction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or by National judgments. 'Tis dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous therefore to be heedleſs of, and reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the holy Ghoſt, ſince the efficacy of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> depends upon him.</p>
               <p>There is a twofold Call of the Spirit <hi>more commune, and more ſpecial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>More commune;</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> many a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called, which never are throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. 'Twas the <hi>commune work</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit which made <hi>Felix tremble;</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought <hi>Agrippa</hi> within a <hi>ſtep of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and cauſed <hi>Herod to do many thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Multitudes of unregenerate ones have fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:107824:25"/> the waters ſtirr'd, the holy Ghoſt moving them to converſion, and readily profering his aid and aſſiſtance; and perhaps for a while they have been led by him: But then ſome luſt or vanity they refuſed to let go, which he has bid them to abandon; they would not turn their ſpiritual ſloth into ſerious diligence about the concerns of their immortal ſouls; and ſo by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarding of his motions, ſlighting of his help, they have made the Spirit to go away <hi>in grief,</hi> that <hi>came in love</hi> to work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a Call of the Spirit, which is <hi>more ſpecial and efficacious;</hi> and when he thus moves them to turn to God, ſinners are not only <hi>almost,</hi> but perſwaded <hi>altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Now the <hi>Method</hi> of the Spirit in working on thoſe who are indeed made Converts, is much to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>1. Thoſe whom the Spirit calls effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, <hi>he convinces of ſin,</hi> Joh. 16. 8. He ſets the <hi>Law</hi> before them, and he himſelf is the Laws Interpreter; and by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary on it they are made to ſee, that the Law forbids not only the breakings forth of ſin at the <hi>lips,</hi> and in the <hi>life,</hi> but alſo the inward luſtings and riſings of ſin in the <hi>heart.</hi> And when the Law thus
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107824:26"/> 
                  <hi>comes,</hi> Oh! how does <hi>the offence abound!</hi> The Spirit ſets <hi>their iniquities in order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes,</hi> and holds their eyes <hi>waking to behold them.</hi> The Book of Conſcience is opened, and how many tranſgreſſions are preſently beheld there regiſtred? And if upon dipping into this book, ſo many abominations do appear, what an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable multitude are down in the book of Gods remembrance? Though ſinners may not conſider it, yet God remembers <hi>all their wickedneſs,</hi> Hoſ. 7. 2. This the ſoul layes to heart; <hi>Innumerable evils compaſs him about,</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>his iniquities take hold upon him,</hi> Pſal. 40. 12. when he lyes down, they lye down; when he riſes, they riſe with him; wherever he goes or is, they continually dog and haunt him.</p>
               <p>If the ſinner have been notorious, how hideous and horrid will ſin appear to him, when all pleas and excuſes are ſilenced, when the painted viſour is pull'd off, and it is ſeen by him in its native complexion? drunkenneſs, uncleanneſs, oaths, profane jeſting, greedineſs after the world, will no longer then be made light of. Theſe and ſuch like, before ſeemed to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of danger, much of delight and pleaſure; but after conviction, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107824:26"/> and damnable nature will be as evident as the Sun at noon-day.</p>
               <p>And though the ſinner has been free from the <hi>more groſs pollutions of the world;</hi> yet enough ſhall be ſhewed him to cauſe him to conclude himſelf a <hi>Wretch,</hi> and in <hi>a loſt eſtate.</hi> What! are all his omiſſions, or mocking of the jealous God, by heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs performances, nothing? Is his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of time and regardleſsneſs of <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> nothing? Is his delighting in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and vanity, and the things of the world, and loving theſe more than God, and Chriſt, and glory, but a ſmall matter? <hi>Theſe</hi> are heinous ſins, which yet the <hi>more civilized</hi> are to be charged with.</p>
               <p>This conviction of the Spirit is <hi>ſtrong and laſting,</hi> wears not off till the ſinner is brought quite home. Actual tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with their aggravations lye heavy; and original ſin, which is the fountain whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne other flow, is diſcover'd. And in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ountain there is <hi>enough</hi> to feed ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd times more ſtreams than have iſſued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth. <hi>David</hi> is not only convinced of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urder and adultery he had committed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut is made to trace theſe ſins to the Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad, the original corruption of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. and the ſight of this,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107824:27"/> how much did it tend to his humiliation?</p>
               <p>Finally, this conviction is not only of ſome <hi>acts</hi> of ſin, but of the badneſs of the ſinners <hi>ſtate;</hi> he is made to ſee himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a <hi>child of diſobedience,</hi> therefore alſo a <hi>child of wrath.</hi> And without cavilling, all is yielded to and acknowledged; with <hi>ſuch evidence</hi> is this conviction of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>2. Thoſe whom the Spirit calls effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, <hi>he works fear in them.</hi> The <hi>ſpirit of bondage to fear</hi> goes before <hi>the ſpirit of adoption.</hi> Of theſe fears and terrors there are degrees indeed, yet <hi>ſuch a meaſure</hi> is wrought in <hi>all</hi> towards whom the Lord has deſigns of love; as to make them <hi>reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſts in a natural eſtate.</hi> Carnal ſecurity is one of the firſt things that is ſtruck at by the Spirit; he bids the ſoul awake, and lets him know that while he ſleeps in ſin; 'tis much more hazardous, than if he <hi>ſlept upon the top of a Maſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well may the ſinner be afraid; <hi>wrath</hi> armed with <hi>irreſiſtible and almighty power,</hi> he has engaged againſt himſelf: <hi>And who can ſtand before Gods indignation? who can abide the fierceneſs of his anger?</hi> Nah. 1. The curſes of the Law have a dreadful ſound in the ſinners ears; and becauſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107824:27"/> threatned, <hi>damnation will not ſlumber long;</hi> the propinquity and neerneſs of ſuch great evils raiſes fear exceedingly. His aſſent is ſtrong; and in his mind he <hi>now</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees <hi>the Lord Jeſus revealed with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, ready to take venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them that know not God and diſobey the Goſpel, and to puniſh them with everlaſting deſtruction,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1. 8, 9. And on thinks he with himſelf, how terrible will it be, to be of the number of them <hi>who ſhall call to the rocks and mountains to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, that they may be hid from the face of him that ſits upon the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb!</hi> This cauſes him to make an halt in his wicked courſe; he dares not ſtill ruſh into ſin, <hi>as the horſe ruſhes into the battel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Thoſe whom the Spirit calls effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, <hi>he raiſes grief and ſorrow in them, becauſe of their ſin and miſery.</hi> They ſee what they have done againſt God, againſt themſelves; and this makes their ſpirits troubled. This is that <hi>being weary and heavy laden</hi> (which the Scripture ſpeaks of) that is in thoſe whom Chriſt calls <hi>to come to him, that they may find reſt unto their ſouls,</hi> Mat. 11. 28, 29. <hi>There was a voice heard upon the high places, weeping and ſupplication
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107824:28"/> of the children of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>becauſe they had perverted their way, and had forgotten the Lord their God;</hi> and this went before their cloſing with his invitation to return, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 21, 22.</p>
               <p>The ſinner by the Spirit is made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſadneſs of his caſe, the evil of his ſin, how miſerably he has been deceived by his luſts and Satan; and ſo his own folly in yielding to them. How does he now accuſe and condemn himſelf? <hi>His heart is grieved, he is pricked in his reins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he has been ſo fooliſh and ignorant, ſo like a beaſt before God,</hi> Pſal. 73. He wiſhes a thouſand times, that temptations had been reſiſted, and that ſin had never been committed. I ſhall repreſent the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the ſinners heart in this <hi>Proſopopoeia. O wretched as I am, What have I been doing all my dayes! Was this the end I was made for, to undo my ſelf? Was there no better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment to be found, than to ad ſin to ſin, and ſo to treaſure up wrath againſt the day of wrath? How much time have I miſpent, and what pains have I taken to make my ſelf miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable! Ah fooliſh ſelf-deſtroying wretch! Doſt thou not ſee how far thou art gone in the broad way; how long ſin has made a meer ſlave of thee; and how bitterly thou haſt provoked the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107824:28"/> Lord to anger? Oh that my head were waters, and my eyes fountains of tears, that I might weep day and night! The damned will weep and wail for ever, and ſhall not I mourn and weep that have ſo highly deſerved to de damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Well may I be troubled, and bowed down greatly, and go mourning all the day long.</hi> Thus the ſinner grieves and bemoans himſelf; and carnal company, ſenſual pleaſures, worldly diverſions cannot drive away this ſorrow; none but he who broke the heart, is able to bind up the wounds of it.</p>
               <p>4. Thoſe whom the Spirit calls effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, <hi>he cauſes to deſpair in themſelves.</hi> They are made to perceive, that they have no power to raiſe themſelves out of thoſe depths of ſin and miſery which they have plunged themſelves into; and as they are <hi>unable</hi> to help themſelves, ſo they ſee that they are <hi>utterly unworthy</hi> to be helped. God may juſtly ſuffer them to <hi>lye</hi> where they are <hi>fallen;</hi> and ſhould he deal thus, they would fall lower and lower till fallen paſt recovery. The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may have recourſe to his duties, hoping by theſe to make <hi>amends</hi> to God, for what he has <hi>done amiſs;</hi> but he is made to ſee, that his beſt duties have ſo much
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107824:29"/> ſin mingled with them; that were it not for <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>interceſſion,</hi> they would be a meer abomination. Now he is beaten off from his own bottom, he has <hi>no confidence in the fleſh</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 3. He can <hi>do</hi> nothing of himſelf; he can claim nothing as his <hi>due</hi> to be done for him, but he muſt be beholding to <hi>grace</hi> for all.</p>
               <p>Upon this he <hi>cryes out of the depths unto the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 130. 1. he perceives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſinking, and cryes, <hi>Lord ſave me, or I periſh. I am at the brink of the bottomleſs pit, and in I ſhall fall, unleſs the hand of mercy catch hold of me.</hi> He begs with <hi>Ephraim, Turn thou me, and I ſhall be turned.</hi> And as the <hi>evil of ſin</hi> is preſented to his view, ſo the <hi>goodneſs of God</hi> is in ſome meaſure by the Spirit diſcovered; and therefore he deſires to be converted, not only upon <hi>neceſſity,</hi> becauſe elſe he would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly and eternally miſerable; but alſo upon choice, becauſe this is the way unto the trueſt happineſs. And theſe <hi>deſires</hi> to be <hi>turned,</hi> are as it were the <hi>firſt breathings</hi> of the new creature. Thus have I ſhewed the manner of the ſpirits operation in thoſe whom he calls effectually to turn to God; as alſo the ſeveral other wayes how
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107824:29"/> the Lord calls upon ſinners to converſion; moſt whereof prove ineffectual, becauſe thoſe that are called are deaf, diſobedient, and gainſaying.</p>
               <p>My work in the <hi>ſecond place,</hi> will be to lay down the reaſons, <hi>Why God does thus call the children of men to turn from their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil wayes and live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſons are ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Hereby he ſhews his gracious nature, that he delights not in the death and deſtruction of his creatures.</hi> Indeed death will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them upon their obſtinate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in evil; but the ſhewing mercy and giving life, is the thing that pleaſes God; therefore he calls the moſt obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to converſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Lord calls us to turn, <hi>that hereby he may inform us of our duty.</hi> We may underſtand from hence that 'tis our duty to go aſtray no longer, but to come to our Fathers houſe with ſpeed; and by the preſſing frequency of the calls, our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to this duty is vaſtly heightned. And truly the diſregarding of our duty in this particular, and the great engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to it; our <hi>refuſing to Turn,</hi> will do us more harm, than <hi>all our other ſins.</hi> All our other ſins, upon our converſion, would
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107824:30"/> be <hi>abundantly pardoned;</hi> but as long as we continue unconverted, not <hi>one</hi> is forgiven, the guilt of <hi>all</hi> does lye upon <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> aſſuredly do lye under wrath.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Lord calls upon us to Turn, <hi>to ſhew that our turning to him will not be in vain.</hi> Though ſin has very much abounded, yet there is not only a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> but a <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> upon our returning, of our being graciouſly received and embraced. And this is matter of great encouragement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſoul who lies under the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin and wrath. Hark what langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is ſpoken unto <hi>Judah!</hi> Jer. 3. 1, 5. <hi>Behold thou haſt ſpoken and done evil things, as thou couldſt, thou haſt play'd the harlot with many lovers;</hi> yet <hi>return again to me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> This call evidently ſhews that their tranſgreſſions though multiplied ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding (if now they would but turn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly) ſhould not be a bar to ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them the door of mercy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord calls upon us to turn, <hi>to intimate 'tis from himſelf, we muſt have power and ſtrength to turn in truth.</hi> The precepts and exhortations in Scripture, to convert, to repent, to believe, to ſtand faſt, and ſuch like, are not delivered, that from hence we might conclude we have power
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107824:30"/> in our ſelves, to do what we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and exhorted to; but they are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, that we might turn theſe precepts into prayers: For inſtance, when we hear the command, <hi>to believe,</hi> it ſhould make us cry out with the ſick childes Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Goſpel. <hi>Lord, help my unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi> When we hear the command, <hi>to caſt away every tranſgreſſion;</hi> it ſhould make us beg with <hi>David, Order my ſteps in thy word, and let not</hi> any <hi>iniquity have the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over me.</hi> When we hear the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>to turn;</hi> it ſhould make us to uſe the language of that penitent, <hi>Jer. 31. 18. Turn thou me and I ſhall be turned; for thou art the Lord my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Lord calls upon us to turn, <hi>to leave the obſtinate without excuſe, who will not turn, who will not come to Chriſt that they may have life.</hi> Of <hi>Iſrael</hi> he ſaith, <hi>All the day long have I ſtretched forth my hand to a diſobedient and gainſaying people,</hi> Rom. 10. <hi>ult.</hi> but this their diſobedience rendred them without apology. When the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>fall into God's revenging hands,</hi> they are the leſs to be pitied, they can have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to plead; becauſe Gods <hi>ſtretching forth his hands,</hi> by way of invitation, in the Goſpel was in vain. Theſe ſinners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107824:31"/> their own ſouls, whoſe neck is like an iron ſinew, who will neither be terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by menaces, nor mollified by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the greateſt kindneſs and mercy; when they are ſummon'd to the bar, how will they be ſtruck <hi>ſpeechleſs,</hi> having not one word to ſay, againſt their own condemnation! They were called unto grace and glory, but they would not hearken. They were told of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but they would not ſeek to prevent it; they were informed of the <hi>wayes of ſin;</hi> and were dehorted from it; nay wooed and intreated with the moſt paſſionate earneſtneſs, not to be cruel to themſelves, by giving way to ſuch a curſed thing; yet they would not conſent to be <hi>freed from ſin, and become the ſervants of righteouſneſs.</hi> And ſurely their <hi>mouths muſt needs be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped;</hi> or if they ſay any thing, when ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is paſſed upon them, it muſt be, to ſide with the juſtice of God againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to acknowledge the equality of <hi>his wayes,</hi> the inequality of <hi>their own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The Lord calls upon us to turn, <hi>that thoſe who are</hi> ordained <hi>to eternal life may be effectually wrought upon, and prevailed with to turn indeed.</hi> We read that the Goſpel was preached both to the Jews and to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107824:31"/> Gentiles, <hi>and as many as were ordained to eternal life believed,</hi> Act. 15. 48. And the truth is, 'tis <hi>much</hi> for the ſake of the <hi>Elect,</hi> who are <hi>ſcattered up and down among the multitude,</hi> that the call to turn is ſo <hi>general</hi> as it is. Hereby thoſe whom the Father <hi>has given to Chriſt</hi> are brought home; and coming home how welcome are they? <hi>Joh. 6. 37. All that the Father giveth me ſhall come to me; and him that comes to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> So much for the reaſons why God calls upon ſinners to turn.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Third place,</hi> I promiſed to explain the nature of this converſion or turning. And I find the Apoſtle does give a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and full deſcription of it, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 18. where he calls it, <hi>A turning from darkneſs unto light, and from the power of Satan unto God.</hi> Hence we gather that converſion lyes in four things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In being turned from darkneſs.</item>
                  <item>2. In being turned unto light.</item>
                  <item>3. In being turned from the power of Satan.</item>
                  <item>4. In being turned unto God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>1. Converſion implies <hi>a being turned from darkneſs.</hi> As <hi>darkneſs was upon the face of the deep, till God ſaid, Let there be light,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107824:32"/> Gen.</hi> 1. 2. So truly, darkneſs overſpreads the ſoul of a natural man, till he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned from above. Believers are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the <hi>power of darkneſs</hi> when <hi>tranſlated into the Sons Kingdom,</hi> Col. 1. 13. which ſhews that ſometimes they were in darkneſs as well as others; and this dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſaid to have a <hi>power,</hi> a power to hold, a power to blind, a power to ruin; ſo that there is a neceſſity of being deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it. Now there be ſeveral kinds of darkneſs, from which they are made free.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Converts are turned <hi>from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ignorance.</hi> No longer are they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be ignorant of the way to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but are made inquiſitive <hi>what they muſt do to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſaved.</hi> They are informed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the doctrine of Chriſt, and are made to underſtand what <hi>believing</hi> and <hi>repenting</hi> mean. They know that ſin is to be ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, as the worſt of evils, and that God is the chiefeſt good; and that <hi>he ſo loved the world, as to give his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believes in him ſhould not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh but have everlaſting life,</hi> Joh. 3. 16. They are made to know that Chriſt is to be received by faith, and that <hi>there is not ſalvation in any other,</hi> and that 'tis in vain
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107824:32"/> to <hi>expect</hi> any thing from him as a <hi>Saviour,</hi> unleſs there be a conſenting to <hi>obey</hi> him as a <hi>Lord.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like truths are no longer hid from them. They are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble now of the miſchief and danger of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; 'tis therefore their deſire to have it in a greater meaſure removed; and they <hi>follow on to know the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Converts are turned from <hi>the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of unbelief.</hi> The Spirit does work a perſwaſion in their hearts, of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain truth of whatever God has revealed in his word. They dare not any longer <hi>make the Lord a lyar,</hi> by not crediting what he has recorded. They believe, and admire, and acknowledge the <hi>Myſtery of God, and of the Father, and of Chriſt,</hi> Col. 2. 2. Heretofore their unbelief did <hi>hide the Goſpel from them;</hi> and concluded them in a <hi>loſt eſtate;</hi> they ſaw not the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of the Word, they were not taken with the <hi>treaſures</hi> of <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> which are there revealed; neither were they awakened by the <hi>terrors,</hi> with which the Word abounds againſt ungodly ones. But now the vail is taken away, and they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, and are affected with what the Goſpel ſpeaks to them. They believe <hi>that God is in Chriſt reconciling the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107824:33"/> himſelf, not imputing their treſpaſſes to them.</hi> And that <hi>being juſtified by his blood, they ſhall be ſaved from wrath through him,</hi> Rom. 5. 9. They believe that ſin is deadly, and the world a cheat, and that ſolid and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs is to be found in God; therefore they leave a <hi>ſhadow</hi> to embrace that which is <hi>ſubſtantial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Converts are turned from <hi>the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of prejudice.</hi> Prejudice raiſes a ſtrange kind of miſt before the eyes, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the light of truth from ſhining into the mind. The <hi>Jews</hi> prejudice againſt Chriſt, was one great thing that blinded them; a principal impediment to their embracing of the Faith. Satan endeavours to fill the ungodly with theſe prejudices, and to keep them up; becauſe by theſe his Kingdom is very much upheld. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſinners are prejudiced againſt <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as if it were <hi>a diſgrace;</hi> whereas it being the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly 'tis the greateſt honour and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which the <hi>rational creature</hi> is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. Sometimes holineſs is lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as <hi>needleſs;</hi> and yet the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that <hi>none ſhall ſee the Lord without it.</hi> Sometimes the carnal heart riſes againſt holineſs, becauſe it imagines, <hi>that nothing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107824:33"/> of delight and pleaſure</hi> is conſiſtent with it; whereas indeed by being converted unto God our <hi>joy</hi> is not <hi>loſt,</hi> but only <hi>changed.</hi> The Kingdom of God is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> but alſo <hi>peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 14. 17. whereas the joy <hi>before</hi> was poor, and low, and bruitiſh, and defiling, being mixed with many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret grudgings of conſcience, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings of heart: <hi>Now</hi> upon converſion, the joy is pure, angelical, ſatisfactory, and an <hi>earneſt</hi> of thoſe <hi>pleaſures which will be for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is this unreaſonable prejudice only againſt the wayes of holineſs, but alſo againſt the <hi>publiſhers</hi> of theſe wayes. There was a prejudice againſt <hi>Elijah,</hi> as if he had been a <hi>troubler of Iſrael;</hi> againſt <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> as if he had been <hi>unfaithful to the State,</hi> and a ſecret friend to the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans;</hi> againſt the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as if they had been intolerable diſturbers, that <hi>had turned the world upſide-down.</hi> And truly the <hi>treaſure</hi> oft-times is diſregarded, though of ſuch ineſtimable value, becauſe of the <hi>veſſel</hi> in which 'tis brought.</p>
               <p>But when any are turned, the miſt of prejudice is immediately ſcattered. <hi>Then</hi> ſtrict doctrine will go down, which before
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107824:34"/> was nauſeated, and made the heart to riſe againſt it; <hi>then</hi> a ſervant of Chriſt will be eſteemed and obeyed, that before was lookt upon as <hi>the filth and off-ſcouring of the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Converts are turned from <hi>the works of darkneſs.</hi> Theſe works are <hi>caſt off,</hi> Rom. 13. 12. No known preſumptuous ſin is allowed of; they perceive the <hi>fruitleſsneſs</hi> of their former wayes, and therefore now <hi>are aſhamed of them, Rom.</hi> 6. 21. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they went on ſecurely in ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they knew not <hi>whither they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> but <hi>now</hi> they perceive the <hi>tendency</hi> of theſe works of darkneſs, even unto <hi>blackneſs of darkneſs for ever;</hi> and ſo <hi>they are made free from ſin;</hi> that is, from ſins ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, <hi>and become the ſervants of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Sin may plead hard againſt its being caſt away; but its pleas are all invalid.</p>
               <p>The gainful ſin does thus plead for it ſelf: <hi>I have raiſed thee from a mean to an high degree, I have filled thy bag, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed thy Table. By</hi> me <hi>thou haſt gotten a fair eſtate, who elſe wouldſt have been little differing from a beggar. And what ſhall I now be caſt off having been ſo beneficial, and yielded ſo much advantage?</hi> But the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert has enough to reply to ſuch a plea.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107824:34"/> 
                  <hi>Whatever he has gained unjuſtly he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore; and if he had truſted in God, and done good, he would have fared better; the Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of unrighteouſneſs is attended with a curſe. And all the while he thrived in a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed way, he was deſtitute of the</hi> true riches; <hi>and 'tis a wonder, by ſuch diſhoneſt gaining of the world, he loſt not his ſoul long ago.</hi> Now therefore he is reſolved againſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful gain, leſt e're he is aware; God, and Chriſt, and his ſoul be loſt beyond reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
               <p>The pleaſing ſin alſo is not without ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, for its being cheriſhed; <hi>I have pleaſed thy fleſh, and rejoyced thy heart; I have made dayes and nights to paſs unſenſibly away, I have gratified thy ſenſes, and made thy tongue to ſing for joy; I have ſtupified and laid that Fury called conſcience, when it has begun to ſtir and torture thee; I have chaſed away thy cares, and made thee to forget thy ſorrows. Time was when the very</hi> thoughts <hi>of me were delightful, and I was embraced as a darling; and why ſhould I now be baniſhed and killed, as if I were an enemy? Is affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſoul, and brokenneſs of heart, to be preferred before the ſweetneſs I was wont to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Converts ear is deaf unto ſuch
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:107824:35"/> Syren-melody; one word is enough to daſh and anſwer all, <hi>That the pleaſures of ſin are but for a ſeaſon,</hi> Heb. 11. 25. but the <hi>pains</hi> of Hell (which without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion are <hi>ſure</hi> to follow) will never have a <hi>period,</hi> nor be in the leaſt <hi>mitigated.</hi> The rich man who had lived jocundly, <hi>fared deliciouſly every day,</hi> when he was caſt into the flames, begged but for <hi>a drop of water,</hi> and 'twas denied him. Therefore the works of darkneſs are caſt off by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of theſe works is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comparable to the <hi>pain,</hi> nor the <hi>gain</hi> to the <hi>loſs,</hi> which will ſpeedily follow.</p>
               <p>2. As this converſion implies a being turned from <hi>darkneſs,</hi> ſo alſo a being <hi>turned unto light,</hi> Eph. 5. 8. <hi>For ye were ſometimes darkneſs, but now are ye light in the Lord, walk as children of light.</hi> And ſo 2 <hi>Cor. 4. 6. God who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined into our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This light has a threefold property, to <hi>diſcover,</hi> to <hi>direct,</hi> to <hi>operate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>This light diſcovers:</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>whatever does make manifeſt is light.</hi> The Convert ſees what he never ſaw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. There may be many toads, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107824:35"/> and other loathſom and hateful creatures in a dungeon, but till the light ſhine in, theſe are not perceived; the breaking in of light diſcovers them: And ſo in the heart of man many impure and noyſom luſts have their abode; but they are not <hi>indeed</hi> acknowledged, neither are they any annoyance, till the <hi>light</hi> does make them manifeſt. The Convert ſees his ſin, his ſhame; he is ſenſible of the plagues of his own heart, and the abſolute neceſſity of a cure. His <hi>intereſt</hi> likewiſe is diſcovered to him; and that is in <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt the Kingdom of God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> in ſecuring his ſoul, which is of far greater value than the world, in mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>one thing needful, that good part which can never be taken away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>This light directs.</hi> It guides thoſe who are turned into the way of peace and truth. The Lamp of the Word (the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit joyning with, and teaching by it) ſhews which are the <hi>perverſe and crooked paths,</hi> to the end, that theſe may be ſhunned and avoided; and it alſo directs into thoſe wayes which are <hi>pleaſing</hi> unto God, and <hi>pleaſant</hi> in themſelves; and moreover, ſo <hi>exceeding ſafe,</hi> that rone ever miſſed of heaven, that continued to tread in them.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107824:36"/> We are <hi>directed to believe</hi> and <hi>to obey;</hi> and where faith and obedience are linked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the off-ſpring of that conjunction will moſt certainly be <hi>glory, honour, and immortality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>This light operates in a powerful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> 'Tis ſuch a light as has heat along with it. Converts were <hi>before told</hi> of the evil, the folly of ſin; but <hi>now</hi> they ſee this by another light, and their hearts are warmed with indignation againſt it. They ſee ſin, ſo as to be deeply <hi>affected;</hi> they ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it, and abhor it. They were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore informed of the mercy and alſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and other perfections of God; but now they have ſuch a view of his glory in the face of Chriſt, as that the fire of love is enkindled, and that love does put them upon labour. When <hi>Caleb</hi> had ſeen the good Land of Promiſe, he was very eager <hi>to go up at once and poſſeſs it,</hi> Num. 13. 30. And truly, when this light has made a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the celeſtial <hi>Canaan,</hi> and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Converts how to get thither: Oh! what watching, whatpraying, whatreſiſting, what ſtriving, what ſtorming will there be?</p>
               <p>3. This Converſion implies a being turned <hi>from the power of Satan.</hi> He is the Spirit that works and rules in the children
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:107824:36"/> of diſobedience, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2. and has poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of them till converted; but <hi>then</hi> he is caſt out, and his ſtrong holds are thrown down. And oh! conſidering the Devils hatred, his power, his ſubtilty; what mercy is it to have the cords, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he led us captive at his pleaſure, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? Three things are comprehended in being turned from the power of Satan.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe who are converted are <hi>freed from Satans dominion.</hi> His uſurped autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they have wiſdom and grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. The promiſe made to them who are not under the Law, but under grace, is this, <hi>That ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall not have the dominion over them,</hi> Rom. 6. 14. And this neceſſarily implies, that Satans dominion ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, for 'tis by the power of ſin he holds it. <hi>The net is now broke, and the ſoul eſcapes as a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler.</hi> The unconverted ſinner, what a ſlave to Satan is he? If the Devil ſay to him <hi>go,</hi> he goes; nay, he <hi>runs,</hi> though it be to his own ruin. The Devil can but <hi>ask and have.</hi> The ſinners time and members, nay and his ſoul too, he can have upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; but the Convert draws nigh to God, and is ſo ſtrengthned by the grace of God, that inſtead of being commanded
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107824:37"/> by Satan, he compels Satan to flee from him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe who are converted, <hi>lay aſide the work of Satan.</hi> They are aware how baſe and injurious, both to God and their own ſouls the devils employments are, and there is a better work than <hi>His;</hi> namely the work of the Lord, which they labour in, and in the doing of which they cannot too much abound.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe who are converted, <hi>Satans baits become deſpicable to them.</hi> 'Tis by means of theſe the devil is ſo powerful. The <hi>God</hi> of this world does make great <hi>uſe</hi> of this world, to bewitch and enſnare the children of men. Senſual delights he exceedingly magnifies, ſumptuous fare, coſtly apparel, credit among men, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant recreations, he ſuggeſts, <hi>How happy will theſe make you.</hi> He tells ſinners of the worth of ſilver and gold, and often through the burning-glaſſes of their eyes, endeavours to ſet their hearts on fire by beauty. But the <hi>Convert,</hi> by the eye of faith, looks higher than theſe things. He is made to ſee the vanity of the creature. He has had impreſſions of divine diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and then the world has appeared an empty bubble, and inſignificant cypher.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107824:37"/> His conſcience was wounded, and when wounded, alas! it was <hi>Nullis medicabilis herbis;</hi> not to be cured by <hi>any</hi> or <hi>all</hi> the things the world could give him.</p>
               <p>The Convert has been made to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and there perceives more durable riches, more laſting pleaſures than the world can brag of; and ſo not the things which are ſeen, but the things which are not ſeen, he is taken with. Though he is <hi>in</hi> the world, yet he looks <hi>beyond</hi> it. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes having reſpect to the recompence of reward,</hi> refuſed to be <hi>called the ſon of</hi> Pharoahs <hi>daughter,</hi> and ſlighted the pleaſures of ſin, and all the treaſures which were in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. This Converſion as it implies a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turned from the power of Satan, ſo a <hi>being turned unto God.</hi> Turn to <hi>me,</hi> ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Lord of Hoſts, and I will turn to you, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1. 3. As it is in Kings Courts; many that come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, buſie themſelves in beholding the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious hangings and the pictures which are there; but the <hi>wiſe Stateſman</hi> minds not theſe; his buſineſs is with the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. In like manner, while moſt of the Creation are taken up wholly with the beholding, and admiring, and purſuing this, and that, and t'other vanity; the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107824:38"/> Convert (who ſhews himſelf herein to be truly wiſe) approaches and has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to <hi>God,</hi> who made theſe things, and can make him more happy, than theſe are able.</p>
               <p>Now when the ſinner turns to God, he looks upon him under a threefold notion, <hi>As a Lord, as a Father, as his ultimate end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. The Convert eyes God <hi>as a Lord.</hi> He owns his Soveraignty, and ſubmits himſelf unto his Scepter. <hi>Other Lords indeed in times paſt have had the dominion over him,</hi> Iſa. 26. 13. but now his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution is fixed and peremptory to own no other Lord but God alone. His will ſtoops unto, and complies with the will of God; when his natural inclination to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any thing is moſt vehement, if the Convert be informed, <hi>That God by that thing will be diſpleaſed;</hi> that's enough to ſtop the current of his deſires. The teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Lord he takes as a rule to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his converſation by. And when he hears that God has commanded him to keep his precepts diligently, his heart preſently ſends forth an eccho back again unto that command, <hi>Oh that my wayes were directed, that I might keep thy Statutes!</hi> Pſal.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107824:38"/> 119. 4, 5. He dares not any longer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly commit the evil which the Word forbids, nor omit the good which the Word commands. Failings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities there are, and will be. <hi>In many things</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>we offend all.</hi> But this evil, that is preſent with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, is a burden to him; and the Law of God is approved and conſented to, and delighted in, as holy, juſt and good. The Convert (which does diſtinguiſh him from an hypocrite) is far from wiſhing that the Law were leſs holy, and that it would allow a liberty to ſin; but he wiſhes that his heart and life were more holy, and to this Law more and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable.</p>
               <p>2. The Convert eyes God <hi>as a Father,</hi> or as <hi>willing</hi> to become his Father in Chriſt Jeſus. 'Twas truly ſaid by one of the Ancients, <hi>Tam Pater nemo, tam puis nemo;</hi> none ſuch a Father as God, none ſo full of fatherly affection; he has ſufficient ſtore to ſupply all the needs of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Prodigals; and he is far more willing to impart of this ſtore, to them which ſee their need, and ask, than earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents can be to give bread unto their hungry children, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 11. This is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107824:39"/> great encouragement to returning. Thoſe Parables of the loſt ſheep, the loſt ſilver, and the loſt ſon, were uttered to this end to hearten ſinners to come home to God, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. The man rejoyced when he had found his ſheep, the woman when ſhe had recovered her piece of ſilver: That kind father, though neceſſity drave his childe home, being ready to periſh in the far Country; and though he came in rags, having waſted all his ſubſtance in riotous living; I ſay, that kind father, as ſoon as ever he ſaw his ſon, ran to him, had compaſſion upon him, embraced him, kiſſed him, cloaths him, adorns him, makes a feaſt for him; and how glad was he that the loſt child was found, that the dead ſon was alive again!</p>
               <p>Surely, we may conclude, that God is willing to receive thoſe that being ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>they have ſinned, and perverted that which is right, and it has not profited them,</hi> Job 33. 27. do with their whole heart return to him. 'Tis true, the Converts ſins and unbelieving heart together, do fill him many times with doubts and fears. He remembers God and is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, becauſe he has ſo bitterly provoked him; he is afraid to call him Father, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:107824:39"/> very much doubts of being received; but then again faith and hope are encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by ſuch kind of promiſes as that which you read of 2 <hi>Cor. 6. 17, 18. Touch not the unclean thing, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, and will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſons and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. The Convert eyes God <hi>as his ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end;</hi> that God may be glorified, that God may be enjoyed is his deſign in turning. The ſinner is ſenſible, that while unconverted, he liv'd to the diſhonour of him that gave him life, and <hi>in whoſe hand his breath is.</hi> Now therefore he has the more zealous deſires to walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing, being fruitful in thoſe works, which are to his praiſe. Before he ſought himſelf, he ſought his own things; he had no higher aim than to gratifie his worldly and fleſhly inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with what his carnal and corrupted mind judg'd to be ſuitable; and ſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf were but profited and pleaſed, he cared not how much the Lord were inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and provoked. But now he is of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mind, he carries on the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign that Angels do, that Chriſt did; namely, to honour and pleaſe the God of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107824:40"/> glory. And not only in his ſpiritual acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, does he aim at this, but alſo in his civil and natural actions and recreations, which hereby become ſpiritualized; he ſeriouſly minds that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 31. Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or what ever ye do, do all to the glory of God.</hi> And now he lives like a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, like a ſon; before he lived like nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, while he lived only to himſelf.</p>
               <p>And by thus glorifying of God, the Convert takes the right courſe to enjoy him. He looks upon God as the beſt por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore pitches upon him. <hi>Let the men of the world take the things of the world, if they pleaſe; let them purſue after bubbles, let them toyl and vex themſelves, for that which when gotten will prove only a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vexation. My ſoul ſeek thou only after God; he alone deſerves thy ſeeking; he alone, when found, can ſatisfie thee to the uttermoſt.</hi> That's now his language.</p>
               <p>Nothing ſhort of God will content the Convert; wealth cannot do it, credit, ſenſual delights cannot do it; nay, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances themſelves are but like empty breaſts, and broken ciſterns, unleſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God be enjoyed in them. He prayes <hi>for God,</hi> he hears <hi>for God,</hi> he
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107824:40"/> faſts <hi>for God,</hi> he comes to the table <hi>for God.</hi> Earth is like Hell, when God is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and Heaven he judges, would not be Heaven if God were not alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Thus have I ſhewed wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion lies, in being turned from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to God.</p>
               <p>I ſhall add a word or two further to manifeſt <hi>through whom</hi> it is that ſinners muſt turn to God, if they would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. And the truth is, 'tis <hi>through Chriſt alone.</hi> The Apoſtle plainly affirms, <hi>That through him both Jews and Gentiles have acceſs by one Spirit unto the Father,</hi> Eph. 2. 18. And our Lord in expreſs terms ſayes, <hi>Joh. 14. 6. I am the way, the truth and the life; no man cometh unto the Father but by me.</hi> 'Tis impoſſible that ſuch guilty and polluted creatures as we have made our ſelves by ſin, ſhould ever be accepted before a juſt and holy God, without a Mediator. Hence it follows, there is a neceſſity we ſhould <hi>look unto Jeſus</hi> (as the Apoſtles phraſe is) <hi>in whom God is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling the world unto himſelf,</hi> 2. Cor. 5. 19. elſe we ſhould not dare to approach, but flie away for fear of being (as we deſerve to be) conſumed.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:107824:41"/>
               <p>Now when we look unto Jeſus the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, we muſt look upon him as our <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as our <hi>Advocate,</hi> as our <hi>Helper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt look upon Chriſt as our <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> This is the Name where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that branch that ſprings from <hi>David</hi> is called, <hi>The Lord our Righteouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 24. 6. There is no coming unto God without ſome righteouſneſs or other. <hi>Our own righteouſneſs is like filthy rags;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe rags, 'tis not able to cover us; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe filthy rags, it cannot adorn or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend us. Therefore we muſt look unto Jeſus to be <hi>made righteouſneſs</hi> to us, that for the ſake of his obedience and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in our ſtead, our ſins may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and our perſons may be accepted in the ſight of God. The righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is imputed to believers, is ſo every way perfect and ſufficient, that the <hi>pure and piercing eye of God can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpy not the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt ſtaw or defect in it.</hi> If therefore we are covered with this, none of our ſins will appear againſt us, or be laid to our charge. <hi>Chriſt hath died,</hi> and upon his death <hi>God doth juſtifie.</hi> Who therefore ſhall accuſe or condemn thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:107824:41"/>2. When we turn to God, we muſt look upon Chriſt <hi>as our Advocate, 1 Joh. 2. 1. If any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father Jeſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi> This Advocate, as he ſuffered to purchaſe pardon and grace, ſo he intercedes that theſe may be beſtowed upon returning ſinners, and God his Father <hi>hears him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</hi> We ought to conſider, and to be encouraged by conſidering, what an High-Prieſt we have at the right hand of God. When the ſinner beholds himſelf, in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf undone, and comes petitioning for remiſſion of ſin, for the healing of his ſpiritual plagues, and for the ſaving of his ſoul, which ſeems to be juſt upon the borders of damnation. This Advocate will take the ſinners petition, and preſent it to his Father, and all ſhall be granted, ay, and infinitely more than the ſinner can deſire or conceive.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When we turn to God, we muſt look upon Chriſt <hi>as our Helper.</hi> He does ſtrengthen the feeble knees, elſe we ſhould not be able to ſet one ſtep in the way to life. The Lord Jeſus is called the <hi>Author of our Faith, Heb.</hi> 12. 2. and by him, <hi>believers are ſaid to have acceſs into that grace wherein they ſtand.</hi> Rom. 5. 2. The
<pb facs="tcp:107824:42"/> ſinner muſt be made ſenſible of his own inſufficiency to turn himſelf, to ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at liberty; and upon this, muſt look unto the Son of God, to bring his ſoul out of priſon, to make him free indeed from the curſe of the Law, from the bondage of corruption, and to enable to come to God, and cleave to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>In the laſt place follows the Application. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. Of Examination.</head>
               <p>Since God calls upon ſinners again and again to turn, <hi>It highly concerns all to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, whether this Call has been obeyed?</hi> 'Tis wiſdom to bring our grace to the Touch-ſtone, ſince there is ſo much coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit grace in the world. As 'tis eaſie and common to miſtake in this matter; ſo there is no miſtake more dangerous, and it won't be long, e're to correct mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes about converſion will be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The damned ſee wherein they did deceive themſelves; but alas! 'tis now too late to think of turning better; the door of mercy is ſhut and barr'd, and will be barr'd for ever. I remember <hi>Theodoret</hi> commenting upon this Text, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that the doubling of the words,
<pb facs="tcp:107824:42"/> 
                  <hi>Turn ye, turn ye,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; gives us to underſtand the ſincerity which is required in converſion. A bare appearance ſets us at a farther di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from God.</p>
               <p>Here I ſhall ſpeak of ſome changes that have a kind of likeneſs to converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which yet are to be found in them, that fall ſhort both of grace and glory.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe cannot be ſaid to be indeed converted, <hi>Who are only turned to ſuch or ſuch a Party, or Opinion, about ſmaller matters in Religion.</hi> Suppoſe thy Opinion be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and right, what's that, if thy heart be not right in the ſight of God? Thoſe who pleaſe themſelves, becauſe they have the name of <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> what does this ſignifie, unleſs they refuſe to conform to the ſinful faſhions and courſes of the world? On the other ſide, They that boaſt of being <hi>Sons of the Church,</hi> what will that advantage them, if by their ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying, and hatred of holineſs, they ſhew themſelves the <hi>Sons of Belial?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe are not indeed converted, <hi>whoſe turning is only partial. Saul</hi> obeyed the command of the Lord in part againſt <hi>Amalek;</hi> that which was vile and refuſe he deſtroyed utterly, but delicate <hi>Agag,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:107824:43"/> the beſt of the ſpoyl he ſpared, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 9. but this partial obedience is cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as high rebellion, <hi>v.</hi> 23. Many will yield to Gods Call in ſome degree; the ſins which they can better ſpare, they will conſent to the mortification of; but the chief, the darling, the delicate ſin, which they live upon, or live ſo ſweetly with. Oh! <hi>That ſhall not be touched<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Herod</hi> was a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Convert; in ſundry reſpects he yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded obedience to the Baptiſt's preaching, but when <hi>John</hi> would have turned him from his inceſt with <hi>Herodias,</hi> this could not be born, but inſtead of obeying this meſſage, he perſecutes, and after kills the meſſenger.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe are not indeed converted, <hi>who only turn to God in the time of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and after are guilty of revolting. Iſrael,</hi> when <hi>Sinai</hi> was all in a fire before their eyes, turned unto God, for fear of being conſumed. Then they cry out, they <hi>will hearken and do what ever the Lord ſhould ſpeak to them,</hi> Deut. 5. 27. But before a few dayes were expired, they quickly turned out of the way which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, and fell into groſs idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. And again we read, <hi>When God ſlew them then they ſought him, they returned &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb facs="tcp:107824:43"/> early after him; and yet all this while their heart was not right, neither were they ſtedfaſt in his Covenant,</hi> Pſal. 78. 34, 37. How many ſick-bed reſolutions have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed like converſion, which upon the return of health have vaniſhed quite away? True converſion is a laſting change; there may indeed be falling fits, and fits of ſlumber: <hi>The wiſe Virgins ſlumbred and ſlept,</hi> Mat. 25. though they were not over wiſe to do ſo. But yet true Converts never go ſo far, as to change their Lord, and to chuſe any thing but God for their chiefeſt happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Reader, beware of being only almoſt a Convert, as thou wouldſt be unwilling, only to be almoſt ſaved, and quite damn'd.</p>
               <p>The queſtion now will be, how may true converſion be diſcerned from all thoſe ſhews, whereby multitudes are deluded? Unto this I anſwer in theſe particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In true Converſion <hi>the heart is turned from the love of every known iniquity.</hi> The ſtrength of ſin lies in the love of it, and love to it plainly argues, that it holds the heart ſtill in poſſeſſion. That's the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts language, <hi>I eſteem thy commands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all things to be right, and I have every
<pb facs="tcp:107824:44"/> falſe way,</hi> Pſal. 119. 128. Thy love is that which God does principally require of thee; if ſin, if the world run away with that, how canſt thou have the face to ſay thou art turned? 'Tis not ſufficient to abſtain from the outward act of ſin, an hypocritical Phariſee may go ſo far; but the very ſoul muſt abhor it: Eſpecially the ſin that has been moſt deſired, moſt delighted in, will be moſt deteſted when converſion is ſincere. The covetous man when turned, will moſt abhor covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the unclean, their filthineſs; the proud, their pride; and the reaſon is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe by theſe ſins God has been moſt diſpleaſed and diſhonoured, and they moſt of all polluted and defiled.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In true Converſion, <hi>there is a renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole man. All things are become new</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. in them that are <hi>new creatures;</hi> and <hi>old things are paſſed away.</hi> The whole man is ſanctified, though not wholly ſanctified; every part is changed, though the change be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. The underſtanding is inlightned, the conſcience is made tender, and has a great command; the heart makes choice of God, the deſires are after his favour and fellowſhip, the members are yielded as
<pb facs="tcp:107824:44"/> inſtruments of righteouſneſs unto holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Convert willingly reſigns and gives up his whole ſelf, both body and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In true Converſion <hi>there is a deſire to be turned more and more;</hi> there is an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring after a greater degree of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The remainders of fleſh are a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and <hi>the ſpirit does luſt againſt them, Gal.</hi> 5. 17. The Convert goes to God, to perfect that which concerns him, to ſtrengthen what he has wrought for him. <hi>Lord! Thou hast done much for me, but there is much more ſtill to do; here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſtill to ſlay, many diſtempers ſtill to heal, many ſpots ſtill to waſh out, many wrinkles ſtill to ſmooth. Oh! Thou who haſt laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, reer up the building, and at laſt bring forth the Top-ſtone, that I may cry,</hi> Grace, grace, <hi>for ever!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In true converſion, <hi>there is a pure and fervent love to Converts. Love to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> is a ſign of being <hi>paſſed from death to life, 1 Joh.</hi> 3. 14. Let them be mean, poor, of weak parts, let them be vilified and deſpiſed by the world; yet if Saints, they will be eſteemed and owned by them that are ſincerely changed. Then our love is right, when the more holy any are, the
<pb facs="tcp:107824:45"/> more we love them; and the more holy deſigns they have upon us, the more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deal with us, for ſin which they ſee in us, ſtill we do the more ardently affect them. Yea, and we can rejoyce in their grace, though becauſe of their luſtre we do ſhine more obſcurely.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In true Converſion, <hi>there is a pity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the unconverted.</hi> Thoſe who are turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed have eſcaped danger, and they cannot but be moved with others peril. How can they chuſe but mourn over their relations and acquaintance, that are without Chriſt and God in the world? Oh, what hazard do ſuch run? when they go to ſleep, they know not but they may wake in the midſt of flames that are unquenchable! when they go out of their houſes they may be in hell before they return! They hang o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the bottomleſs pit, by the ſmall thread of their lives; and a thouſand things may happen every day ſufficient to break that thread aſunder, and then in they fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out redemption. Oh doleful ſtate of the ungodly! If thou who art a religious Wife, ſhouldſt wake in the night, and find thy Husband ſtone dead by thee, would it not extreamly amaze and grieve thee? Or if thou who art the Maſter of a
<pb facs="tcp:107824:45"/> family ſhouldſt find all thy children and ſervants of a ſudden dead before thy eyes; would not thy heart be extreamly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And ſurely if thy Husband, thy Wife, thy Children, thy Servants, are dead in ſins, in danger of being for ever damned, much more reaſon haſt thou to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for them, and to endeavour by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, and prayers, and tears, to have them turned and reconciled unto God.</p>
               <p>Now Reader, Try thy ſelf by theſe ſigns of Converſion; if thou findeſt them in thy ſelf, thou mayeſt rejoyce, for theſe plainly ſhew, that thy name is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book of Life. But, if any ſin be loved, if thy mind, and conſcience, and heart, and life be all defiled; and as thou art unrenewed, ſo thou haſt no deſire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter renewing grace; if thou delighteſt in the carnal, and art an hater of Saints. This ſhews, to converſion thou art a ſtranger, and to this hour art in the gall of bitterneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> II. Of Terror.</head>
               <p>Whoever thou art, high or low, rich or poor, male or female, that readeſt theſe lines, and waſt never turned. I am ſent
<pb facs="tcp:107824:46"/> to thee from God with heavy tydings; ſuch, as if thou wert not a bruit, a ſtock, would make thee like <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> when upon the view of the hand-writing upon the wall, <hi>his countenance was changed, his thoughts troubled him, the joynts of his loyns were looſed, and his knees ſmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e one againſt another,</hi> Dan. 5. 6. I am to prophecy not good concerning thee, but evil. I have <hi>a roll</hi> to deliver thee, but 'tis <hi>written with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without with lamentation, and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wo.</hi> Thou art perhaps jolly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, but this is like the mirth and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a ſick man out of his ſenſes, which argues his diſtemper to be the ſorer. Alas! ſinner, Thou haſt not reaſon ſo much as once to ſmile while in a ſtate of nature. How many threatnings are denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee? And ſuppoſe thou wert ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Cannons, all ready at once to be diſcharged at thee, theſe would be nothing neer ſo dreadful as the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and curſes which the juſt and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God has uttered. Open thy eyes and look which way thou wilt, enough may be perceived to cauſe thy heart to meditate terror; above, an angry God; below, a flaming Hell; behind, an innumerable hoſt of ſins purſuing thee; before, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb facs="tcp:107824:46"/> and the world leading thee along in the broad way to deſtruction.</p>
               <p>But more particularly, I would have theſe following Truths laid to heart.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whilſt thou art unconverted thou art alſo unpardoned.</hi> Thou ſtandeſt indebted many thouſand talents, and not ſo much as one mite of all that debt is paid. The leaſt tranſgreſſion does make thee liable to the curſe of the Law, and gueſs then what an accurſed wretch thy many and thy mighty ſins have made thee? Upon thy <hi>returning &amp; acknowledging of thy iniquity,</hi> God has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to do it away, he will lay the load upon the back of a Mediator; but if thou wilt not conſent to be turned, thou alone muſt bear it. Sin is another kind of thing than thou imagineſt. <hi>Adams</hi> firſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in eating the forbidden fruit, which was aggravated becauſe he would have been as God; and he believed the Serpent, and made God a lyar, and which was indeed a rejecting of the whole Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of life made with him: Oh! how did it make himſelf to ſmart? and not only himſelf, but his whole progeny are the worſe for it. And if one ſin has brought a curſe upon all the children of men; think, O ſoul, how thou wilt be
<pb facs="tcp:107824:47"/> able to ſtand under all the ſins thou haſt committed. Sin does make the whole Creation groan, it makes the damned to lament and to deſpair, and will be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable load for ever; ſin was found heavy by our Lord, this cauſed his Agony, and made his ſoul exceeding ſorrowful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto death. Nay, God himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, that he is preſſed with iniquity, as a Cart is preſſed, which is full of ſheaves. And wilt thou ſinner make light of it? Oh! how heavy wilt thou one day feel it?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Whilſt unconverted thou art treaſuring up more and more wrath againſt the day of wrath.</hi> Thy ſcores are large already, but every day thou runneſt on the ſcore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh; every day thou makeſt new wounds, though conſcience now be ſo ſtupid that it feels nothing. As thy ſin abounds, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably the vials of divine indignation grow fuller, which will at laſt be all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptied upon thy head. Unnatural cruelty to be a Devil to thy ſelf! to be thy own ſouls murderer! Thou art continually ſetting thy ſelf at a greatter diſtance from God, and engaging him more and more againſt thee, who alone can be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and ſalvation to thee. Thou wilt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107824:47"/> at laſt, thou haſt been thy own foe, and acted to thy own confuſion, <hi>Jer. 7. 19. Do they provoke me to anger, ſaith the Lord, do they not provoke themſelves to the confuſion of their own faces?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Whilſt unconverted, thou rendereſt thy ſelf more and more unmeet for glory and bleſſedneſs.</hi> The more impure thou art, the more unfit alſo to ſee God. The abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations which are loved and wrought by thee, do make thee an improper inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant for the new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance above is an <hi>inheritance of Saints,</hi> 'tis, as an <hi>incorruptible,</hi> ſo an <hi>undefiled inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 4. The company is all holy, and ſo are the employments. There is not a vain or ſinful word ſpoken there; nor an impure deſire or thought to be found in any that are above. And what wouldſt thou do there among them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a change be wrought in thee.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>If thou turneſt not thou art ſure to die:</hi> As life is far off, ſo death is neer. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, <hi>That God is angry with the wicked every day; and if he turn not, he hath wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t his ſword, he hath bent his bow and made it ready,</hi> Pſal. 7. 11, 12. And when the inſtruments of death are thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prepared, 'tis a ſign God will make quick work, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:107824:48"/> ſuddenly cut the offender off. <hi>Death</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>a King of Terrors;</hi> and it well deſerves that name, in reſpect of the ungodly. Then their good things are all received, and the evils come upon them, which will never be removed; their torments begin, which will never know an end. <hi>So long as God is God, to have God their enemy; ſo long as God is happy, to lye in extreameſt miſery!</hi> What tongue can utter, or heart imagine the horror of this? An angry ſin-revenging Lord will lay load upon thee, and yet keep thee from ſinking into nothing; he will uphold thee in thy being, that thou mayeſt be for ever plagued. He will ſhew his mighty power, in holding thee up with one hand, that he may laſh thee with the other, unto all eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> III. Of Conſolation.</head>
               <p>You who have obeyed the Call of God to turn, I am commanded to ſpeak peace and comfort to you, <hi>Iſa. 40. 1. Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, ſaith your God.</hi> The unconverted are not more accurſed than you are bleſſed. I have ſeveral things to tell you, which are enough to make your hearts leap for joy.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:107824:48"/>1. <hi>God hath had thoughts of love towards you before the foundation of the world was laid.</hi> He did <hi>predeſtinate and chuſe you unto the adoption of children,</hi> Eph. 1. long before you were. From everlaſting he did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to make you his Heirs, and joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs with Chriſt unto that Kingdom and Glory, with which the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. And ſince the love of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you is from everlaſting, is co-eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal with himſelf, ſurely it can never in time be changed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>God hath juſtified you freely by his grace, through the redemption of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 3. 24. <hi>As far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo far are your iniquities removed from you, Pſal.</hi> 103. 12. and ſurely that's as far as you can deſire. They are <hi>caſt into the depth of the Sea;</hi> which argues, when they come <hi>to be ſought for, they ſhall not be found;</hi> juſt as thoſe things which are caſt into the depth of the Sea, we deſpair that ever they ſhould be recovered. <hi>Chriſt has been wounded for your tranſgreſſions, he has been bruiſed for your iniquities,</hi> Iſa. 53. 5. And as the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Imputation of your ſins to Chriſt did cauſe him to undergo real ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; ſo, the imputation of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:107824:49"/> to you, will cauſe a real exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption from that wrath and puniſhment which by ſin you have juſtly merited. Be of good cheer Converts, your ſins are forgiven, and conſequently the curſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and alſo the ſting of death is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>You that are Converts it won't be long e're you are all glorified,</hi> Rom. 8. 30. <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, whom he did predeſtinate them he alſo called, and whom he called them he alſo juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and whom he juſtified them he alſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> The Lord has promiſed, that thoſe who overcome ſhall ſit with him on his Throne. You ſhall not only overcome, but be <hi>more than conquerors through him that has loved you.</hi> Manſions are already prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, and when you are prepared for thoſe Manſions, you ſhall be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Then, neither the fury nor the favour of the world will be a temptation. Satans fiery darts will not be able to reach you, when once you are gotten into the third Heaven. When you are juſt entring into the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> you will ſhake hands both with ſin and miſery at the door, and neither of theſe will be able to follow. <hi>Tears will be wiped away,</hi> and all cauſe of ſorrow will be gone; there will
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:107824:49"/> be a clear view of God, without the leaſt cloud; the Sun of righteouſneſs will ſhine for ever without any eclipſe, there will be intire joy without grief, perfect peace without any trouble, compleat ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs without the leaſt remainder of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, a full bleſſedneſs without period<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> IV. Of Exhortation.</head>
               <p>And who would not now become a Convert? Have you any thing to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a pardon, or againſt that glory which has been revealed? Shall it be made a queſtion, whether pleaſures for evermore, or eternal torments are to be preferred? Oh that you would come to your ſelves! and then I am ſure you would come to God immediately.</p>
               <p>The Arguments to perſwade you to Converſion are divers.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>If you turn not, you cannot anſwer the end of your Creation.</hi> You muſt not think God gave you a being, and ſent you into the world, to pleaſe your ſelves, to ſatisfie your inordinate and corrupt deſires, and to live careleſly and rebelliouſly againſt him; but thus you will do till you are converted. Did the Lord give you an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:107824:50"/> faculty, and not deſign that he ſhould be underſtood and known by you? Did he give you a memory, and not intend that he ſhould be remembred? Did he give you an heart to love and to deſire, and not deſign himſelf to be the chief ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of both? Did he give you affections that you ſhould give them away to ſin and vanity? Oh croſs not any longer the end for which you were made, leſt you cauſe the Lord <hi>to repent and be grieved at the heart he made you,</hi> Gen. 6. 6. and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to deſtroy the workmanſhip of his own hands. If you continue obſtinate and without underſtanding, <hi>He that made you will not ſave you, or have mercy on you; he that formed you will ſhew you no favour,</hi> Iſa: 27. 11.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Unleſs you turn, you cannot anſwer the end of the death of Chriſt, and the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wrought thereby.</hi> Our Lord died not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to expiate offences, but alſo to purifie unto himſelf a peculiar people, zealous of good works; and <hi>that in the body of his fleſh, through death, he might preſent them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unblameable,</hi> Col. 1. 22. <hi>Through the eternal Spirit, he offered up himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot to God, that by his blood he might purge our conſciences from dead works, to ſerve the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:107824:50"/> living God,</hi> Heb. 9. 14. From theſe and and ſuch like places it evidently follows, that not only our pardon, but our purity was deſigned by the Lord Jeſus. But how can we be pure, unleſs we turn to God from ſin which does defile us? Chriſt knew what a ſickneſs and debaſement of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſin is; therefore he himſelf was ſlain, that ſin might be killed. And will you dare to live in ſin? Hark to the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 24. Who his own ſelf bare our ſins in his body on the tree, that we being dead to ſins ſhould live unto righteouſneſs, by whoſe ſtripes ye were healed.</hi> And as the death of Chriſt is an argument to perſwade to turn from ſin, ſo from this death vertue and power is to be derived, whereby ſin may be ſubdued.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>You are further obliged to turn, becauſe of Gods condeſcenſion in giving you leave to do it.</hi> If the gulph had been fixed upon the very firſt tranſgreſſion; if the turning of fallen man had been as impoſſible, as the turning of the fallen Angels; the Lord could not have been charged with the leaſt injuſtice. But although you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted; he calls after you. Without any detriment or prejudice to his juſtice, he has found out a way to ſhew you mercy.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:107824:51"/> The Devils were never called to conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; as ſoon as ever they had ſinned they were fettered in chains of darkneſs that ſhall never be unlooſed. But hark what wiſdom ſayes, <hi>Prov. 8. 4. Unto you, O men I call, and my vow is to the ſons of man.</hi> You have often ſtopt your ears, Oh that at laſt you would hear, that your ſouls may live. The long deafning of your ears may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to ſhut his mouth; and then you will never be converted, never healed.</p>
               <p>4. Conſider, <hi>Who 'tis that calls upon you to turn; and what is his deſign in it.</hi> You are undone wretches, who have neither skill, nor will, nor power to ſave your ſelves. And he that calls after you is a God to whom power and mercy does belong. And his deſign is to make his power and mercy known in you. His aim is, to bring you neer, that he manifeſt himſelf to you, as he does not manifeſt himſelf unto the world; to ſhield you from danger, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your needs, according to the riches of his glory, to deliver you from every evil work, and to preſerve you to his heavenly Kingdom. And is there any harm in all this?</p>
               <p>5. <hi>'Tis unreaſonable that the world or ſin
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:107824:51"/> ſhould be an hindrance, and any longer ſtave you off from God.</hi> Well may you turn from ſin, for that deſerves your hatred; well may your hearts turn from idolizing the world and the things of it, for theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your ſcorn. All things beſides God, are either hurtful or helpleſs. Nothing more hurtful than ſin; and they that have expected help from the creatures, have found themſelves deſtitute and forlorn in their extremity.</p>
               <p>6. <hi>If you turn to God, he will not fail to turn to you.</hi> His ear ſhall be turned, and be open to your cry; his hand ſhall be upon you for good; and in the hollow of his hand you ſhall be ſecure; he is greater than all, and none ſhall be able to pluck you out of his hands; he will not hide, but turn his face towards you; he will give peace as well as mercy, he will let you know that pardon is multiplied, that your love alſo may be increaſed. The debtor loved much, to whom much was forgiven. Finally, the ſtream of his benefits ſhall be turned towards you. The Lord will do you good, and delight in doing ſo. Temporal things you ſhall not want, ſpiritual bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhall be ſhowred down abundantly, and at laſt you ſhall aſcend, and be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:107824:52"/> into his immediate preſence, where God will turn to you, ſo as never to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw more. Be not afraid or diſmayed whoever turn againſt you for converſion ſake. The Lord himſelf is with you, and for you, and he will turn to good what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries do mean for evil.</p>
               <p>7. <hi>Not only his Word, and Miniſters, and Spirit, but alſo his Providences call upon you to turn to God.</hi> Both his mercies and his judgments do preſs this exhortation to converſion. The ſtreams of goodneſs that continually run towards you, and which ſometimes ſwell and overflow abundantly, do ſignifie that 'tis your wiſdom to forſake the broken ciſterns, and come to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living waters. His mercies ſpeak this language, that 'tis good to return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and obtain an intereſt in the Father of them. Then theſe mercies will be in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Cords of love are caſt about you on purpoſe to draw you unto the God of love and peace. Oh that you would run to him! The riches of his goodneſs are unlocked and diſcovered, <hi>that hereby you may be led unto repentance,</hi> Rom. 2. 4.</p>
               <p>His judgments likewiſe are inflicted in purſuance of the ſame deſign. That is the voice that's uttered by them; <hi>Go return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:107824:52"/> the Lord, for he hath torn and he will heal you; he hath ſmitten, and he will bind you up, Hoſ.</hi> 6. 1. The Fire of <hi>London</hi> calls upon the Inhabitants of it, and of the whole Land, ſince they have not only heard of God by the hearing of the ear, but their eyes have ſeen him marching out ſo dreadfully againſt them, to abhor them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to repent in duſt and aſhes. Thoſe many thouſands which were cut off by the plague of Peſtilence, although they are dead, they ſtill ſpeak; and that which they ſay is this. <hi>Oh you that are alive, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, return unto the Lord your God, for after death 'twill be too late to do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>8. Conſider, <hi>As yet 'tis not too late to turn to God.</hi> Though hitherto ſtupid, if now you will awake, though hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory; if now you will yield your ſelves to the Lord, though hitherto you have ſhut the door to keep in ſin, and to keep out Chriſt; if now at laſt you will open at the knock of the Goſpel, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that your luſts ſhould be expelled, and the Lord Jeſus enter; he is ready to receive you into grace and favour, and all former denials, affronts, repulſes, ſhall be forgotten and forgiven. The Scepter is ſtill held forth, the Lord is not removed
<pb facs="tcp:107824:53"/> from the Mercy-ſeat; mercy and grace may now be had, if you will come for it. But if you will not know when you are well offered, and are reſolved not to ceaſe from your ſtubborn way; an oath may ſoon be ſworn in wrath, that you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into Reſt; and God may ſay, <hi>He that's filthy, let him be filthy ſtill; he that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill; he that is joyned to the profits and pleaſures of the world which he makes his idols, let him alone; he that deſpiſes the offer of grace, ſhall not have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offer; he that now refuſes to be converted ſhall never be a Convert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh that I could prevail by all theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. But leſt they ſhould take no impreſſion, leſt they ſhould ſlip out of your minds, and have no influence upon your hearts, I ſhall ſecond them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With a voice from Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With a voice from Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With a voice from Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. <hi>With a voice from Hell.</hi> Imagine therefore, a damned ſinner, who has lain many years in the burning lake, ſhould have leave to come and appear in the face of this aſſembly; and a river of tears ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt guſhed out of his eyes, and for a while ſtopt his expreſſions, he at length ſhould thus ſpeak to you.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:107824:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curſed be the day wherein I was born, and that night wherein it was ſaid there is a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child conceived! Let that day be darkneſs, let not God regard it from on high, neither let the light ſhine upon it. Alas, 'twere better never to have been at all, than to be for ever miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble! How intolerable are the gNawings of the never dying worm? how hot and unquenchable are thoſe flames, which the breath of the Lord as a ſtream of brimſtone doth kindle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The world is extreamly miſtaken in ſin. They think it light and pleaſant, and ſo I thought once, as well as they; but now I find how wofully I was deceived; I feel ſins weight, and taſte, yea am drunken with the gall and wormwood of it. I find that true, which before I was told, but would not believe, that 'tis a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God. His mighty hands have taken hold of me, and bound me hand and foot, and thrown me into outer darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And there I muſt lie tortured to</hi> Eternity! <hi>Oh that word does rend my very heart, kills all hope, ſinks and quite overwhelms me in ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion. If after millions of millions of ages my torments were to end, I ſhould ſtrengthen my ſelf under my ſorrows; but ſince after ſo long a ſpace of time I ſhall be as far from releaſing, as the firſt moment I was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:107824:54"/> this is that which makes my grief to know no bounds, becauſe my miſery knows none. Oh what phrenzy poſſeſs'd me, that for the ſake of a little gain and pleaſure, for a ſhort ſeaſon, which ſin did yield me, I ſhould venture to dwell with devouring fire, and to inhabit everlaſting burnings!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I muſt only blame my ſelf; God is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, but not in the leaſt unrighteous. He cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but I refuſed, he ſtretched forth his hand, but I diſregarded him, I ſet at nought all his counſel, and would none of his reproofs; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member very well, he ſpake to me often to turn out of the paths that lead to deſtruction and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; but I would needs go on. I was warned to flie from the wrath to come, but I would take no warning. I was intreated to be reconciled, but reſolved to continue a rebel. I would not be made clean, though the Lord waited to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, and frequently ſaid, When will it once be!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what! Will any of you continue in the ſame deſperate mind that I was of? Will you ſtill cheriſh the ſelf-ſame ſins for kind that were my undoing? Behold the flam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> about my ears, and oh that you could conceive the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of my heart! Be wiſe, be wiſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of mercy and ſalvation while 'tis tendered to you; for if once you come to this place of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:107824:54"/> torment, the Lord will forget to be gracious, and his mercy will be quite and clean gone for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>A voice from Heaven.</hi> Suppoſe one of the glorified Saints who has been an Inhabitant of the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who has converſed with an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Angels, and has ſeen God face to face; ſhould for a while leave his bliſsful Manſion, and having abundance of joy and glory in his looks, ſhould utter ſuch kind of language as this before you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh the height, and length, and depth, and breadth of the love of Chriſt which paſſes knowledge! How unſearchable is his goodneſs, and his mercy paſt finding out! Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain, to receive power, and riches, and wiſdom, and ſtrength, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, and bleſſing; for by his blood he has redeemed me, with millions more, out of every kindred, and tongue, and people, and Nation! I was called to turn and live, and through rich grace was enabled to obey the Call; and now I find what a glorious life that is, unto which ſincere and perſevering Converts ſhall at laſt be brought. This is a life that's free from ſin, and free from ſuffering, that will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee death, or be in danger of the grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis beſt of all to be neer to God. Chriſt is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:107824:55"/> without all controverſie the beſt Maſter, to be ſubject to him it is to reign, and reign for ever! What ails the blind and ſtupid world, that they ſee no form nor comlineſs in this faireſt among ten thouſand, the light of whoſe countenance makes heaven not to need the light of the Sun, or Moon, or Stars! His beauty is all-ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, his grace is much more precious than gold that periſhes; but his glory, 'tis not lawful, or poſſible for me to utter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now will any of you any longer ſlight him? Open your eyes and ſee evidently that you are the children of perdition, the ſons of death without him; but through him you may be turned, through him you may be ſaved, with a great and everlaſting ſalvation. Surely then you have reaſon to value him above all; though the whole world, nay though ten thouſand worlds ſhould ſtand in competition with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. <hi>Hear a voice from Chriſt himſelf.</hi> Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the Lord Jeſus appearing with a light far above the brightneſs of the Sun. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome of his Angels as his Harbingers and forerunners, coming before him, and crying, <hi>Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts;</hi> and at laſt himſelf viſibly filling this place with his Majeſty and with his glory, and having ſtricken an awe into you, and wrought in you an admiration of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:107824:55"/> and greatneſs, ſuppoſe him thus ſpeaking and pleading with you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Look unto me and be ye ſaved all ye ends of the earth, I am your Redeemer, and there is none elſe; you have deſtroyed your ſelves, but in me, and me alone, you may find help; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I make you free, ſin will ſtill reign in you, and if it reign, it will alſo ruine; unleſs I binde the ſtrong man armed, he will keep you bound, and lead you captive at his pleaſure; unleſs I turn, and bring you neer to God, you will run farther and farther away from him, till at laſt there be no poſſibility of returning. How long ye ſimple ſouls will ye love ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and fools hate knowledge? Turn ye at my reproof; behold I will pour out my ſpirit upon you, I will make known my words unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Former contempts I will paſs by, if now at laſt you will receive me. I will free you from the guilt, and from the power of ſin, I will pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie my Fathers anger, though by breaking his Laws, and deſpiſing me his Son, you have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much incenſed him. Though by nature captives, I will make you Kings and Prieſts; though by ſin traitors and enemies, I will make you Sons, and heirs of God, and coheirs with my ſelf, who am the Heir of all things. You ſhall in no caſe be miſerable, if all that fulneſs which dwells in me can ſatisfie and make you happy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:107824:56"/>
               <p>And after all this, my brethren, will you be fond of ſin and ruine? Oh hear the voice of the Son of God, who is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you ſhould periſh.</p>
               <p>How ſhall I do to work upon you? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I could be willing that theſe words ſhould be my laſt, upon condition they might be powerful and effectual to the converting, and healing, and ſaving all that are within the ſound of them. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I could be willing to expire here, and be carried dead out of the Pulpit, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition all you might hear, ſo as to turn from your evil wayes and live. Moſt of thoſe thouſands which are before me are unknown to me: But this I know, that you all have ſouls, and that every ſoul is worth a world. Oh that you all would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult your ſouls intereſt and ſafety!</p>
               <p>But leſt it ſhould be in vain, if I only ſpeak to you, I ſhall direct my words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him who is Lord over all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And oh that he who works, and none can let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r hinder, would work a thorow ſaving change in you! Oh that he would pity thoſe among you, who are unto your ſelves cruel! Oh that he would awaken the ſouls, that are not only aſleep, but dead! and break the hearts which have made themſelves as an Adamant ſtone!
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:107824:56"/> Oh that he would convince you of your ſin and miſery, and effectually turn you from the one, that you may be for ever freed from the other!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe Petitions let every heart ſay, Amen!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> V. Of Direction.</head>
               <p>I would believe by this time, that you are willing to hearken unto, and likewiſe follow ſome directions, how to become ſincere Converts. Directions how to get eaſe when you are in pain; how to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver health, when you are ſick; or an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tate which you have loſt, I am confident would be heeded. And are not directions from the infallible word of truth, how to be turned and ſaved, of far greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence?</p>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>The Directions are theſe which follow.</head>
                  <p>1. <hi>Think upon, and with a ſerious ſpirit conſider your wayes.</hi> This <hi>Conſideration</hi> had great influence upon the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 119. 59. I thought on my wayes, and turned my feet unto thy teſtimonies. I made haſte and delayed not,</hi> &amp;c. That injunction is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 5. And again, <hi>v. 7. Thus
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:107824:57"/> ſaith the Lord of hoſts, Conſider your wayes.</hi> And that paſſage, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 14. is to be obſerved. <hi>Now lo, if he beget a Son that ſeeth all his fathers ſins which he hath done, and conſidereth and doth not ſuch like,</hi> &amp;c. If ſinners would but conſider what they do, when they do evil, it would be a means to make them ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well. Conſider the miſery and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being at a diſtance from God. The wayes which naturally you walk in, do lead you away from him; and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayes, <hi>Thoſe that are far from God ſhall periſh, he will deſtroy all them that go a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from him,</hi> Pſal. 73. 27. Think of theſe things ſo long, till you find your hearts affected, ſo as to conclude it height of madneſs to lye ſecure in an unconvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtate. Let this thought take deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. <hi>All the while thou perſiſteſt in thy evil wayes, thou for ſakeſt the Lord, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakeſt thy own mercies, and art travelling apace to the regions of eternal wo and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Study the vanity of former excuſes.</hi> I know the natural mans mouth is very full of them, but 'tis very eaſie to anſwer them.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:107824:57"/>
                  <p>Sin, thou ſayeſt, is rivited in thy very nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore thou hadſt need to cry to heaven, that thy nature may be changed, and to be made a new creature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſin is the commune practiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore thy danger is the greater, and thou ſhouldſt be the more careful, leſt thou be overwhelmed in that r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in that will be ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But my luſts are both profitable and pleaſant, and why then ſhould I abandon them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſider ſoul whether the damned who have loſt their ſouls and eternal bleſſedneſs, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the vengeance of eternal fire, have any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to boaſt of gain or pleaſure?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But men will deride and ſcorn me, if I become a Convert.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They that do ſo are beſides themſelves, and ſober people uſe not to be concerned at the laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch as are out of their wits. Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tèmn their contempt, deſpiſe the ſhame they coſt upon you; ſhortly they themſelves will wiſh, that inſtead of ſcorning at, they had been imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to turn unto and follow God is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard, and the difficulty is a very great diſcouragement.</p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:107824:58"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The work is hard indeed, but the ſtrength and aſſiſtance is great, which ſhall be afforded. The Lord will work all your works in you and for you,</hi> Iſa. 26. 12. <hi>He commands no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what he is ready to help you to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if I am a Convert, I ſhall never live a pleaſant hour; my tears will be my meat and drink, and my ſorrows my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual companions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Oh groſs miſtake! and unreaſonable preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt the wayes of holineſs! If godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be ſo melancholy a buſineſs; why does the Scripture tell us of peace which paſſeth all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and joys that are unſpeakable and full of glory? Why is</hi> David <hi>ſo often ſinging, ſo often harping, if mirth and Religion were <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, altogether inconſiſtent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh but if I turn, I ſhall be expoſed to ſuffering.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, ſuppoſe thou art, the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the preſent grace and conſolation, which will attend thy trials, much leſs with the glory that ſhall be revealed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Study the vanity of all ſuch excuſes.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>Save your ſelves from the untoward ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration you live among.</hi> This was the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:107824:58"/> the Apoſtle gave to them that had been awakened and <hi>pricked in their heart, Act.</hi> 2. 40. You muſt ſhake hands with your former brethren in iniquity, elſe they will be a great temptation and ſnare to you. Carnal company are incarnate devils, who endeavour to draw as many as they can to Hell along with them. Therefore the wiſeſt of men does uſe ſo many words of caution, <hi>Prov. 4. 14, 15. Enter not into the path of the wicked, and go not in the way of evil men; avoid it, paſs not by it, turn from it and paſs away.</hi> Though you are not bound to be moroſe and unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil towards the ungodly, take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delightfully familiar. Many a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and good reſolution has cooled and vaniſhed, by our lighting into the ſociety of the wicked. Suck not in any prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from them againſt true piety; and when they preſume to prate againſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, hearing, faſting, profeſſing, when they quarrel againſt the Lord's day, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Lord's people; look upon all this, but as the ravings of ſuch as are in a ſpiritual ſenſe diſtracted.</p>
                  <p>4. <hi>Deſpiſe not Prophecyings.</hi> The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Word is ordained on purpoſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:107824:59"/> to work faith, and to turn ſinners unto God; and therefore let not drowſineſs, diſtraction, cares, or pleaſures, or luſts, or the deceitfulneſs of riches choak this Word, and hinder it from proſpering to this end whereunto it is appointed. When <hi>Ezekiel propheſied over the dead and dry bones,</hi> they preſently revived, and a valley of dead bones became a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Army. And who knows while thou art propheſied over, by the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, but of a ſudden thou mayeſt be made alive, who waſt dead in treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Let powerful preaching be prized and frequented by you: Certainly the word has a converting power when 'tis ſet home, <hi>Pſal. 19. 7. The Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul; the teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. <hi>Quench not the Spirit,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 19. His conviction you muſt not ſtifle, but improve. The Spirit of the Lord ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times approaches very neer unto a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, a ſwearer, a covetous worldling, an unclean perſon, and tells them, the way they take it is perverſe before him, that there is but a ſtep between them and death, between them and damnation; and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:107824:59"/> therefore moves them to humiliation, and to reformation. He informs them they had better leave their ſins, than be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done for their ſake. Now ſuch convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might be heightned into Converſion, if they were but cloſed with, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. But thouſands reſiſt the holy Ghoſt; they had rather be permitted to ſin without diſturbance, than to have the waters troubled, though upon ſtepping in, they might be healed, what ever their ſpiritual malady and plague be. Doſt thou find the Spirit neer thee; Oh heed his checks, comply with all his motions, and beg that thou mayſt not be put off with commune operations; but that a ſaving work may be wrought in thee!</p>
                  <p>6. <hi>Lay hold upon and plead the Lords own Covenant.</hi> In this Covenant he has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged <hi>to give you a new heart, to cleanſe you from your filthineſs and your idols; to put his Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walk in his Statutes;</hi> that is, in one word to <hi>convert you,</hi> Ezek. 36. 25, 26, 27. Be earneſt that theſe promiſes may be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. Reſolve to take no nay, the Lord will be pleaſed with your importunity, in a matter which 'tis ſo much for his own
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:107824:60"/> honour to grant you. You cannot turn your ſelves, but he can as eaſily do this work, as leave it undone. One word of life and power will raiſe you. And ſince he ſayes, <hi>Turn ye, turn ye from your evil wayes, for why will ye die, O houſe of</hi> Iſrael; preſently make this Text into a prayer. <hi>Turn us, turn us from our evil wayes, for why ſhould we die, O thou God of Iſrael!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
